<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-12-11T16:42:46+01:00</updated><id>https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bene’s Blog</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to computer science, education, music, philosophy and technology</subtitle><author><name>Benedikt Zönnchen</name><email>benedikt.zoennchen@web.de</email></author><entry><title type="html">The Disruption of Education</title><link href="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2022/12/10/disrupting-education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Disruption of Education" /><published>2022-12-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2022/12/10/disrupting-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2022/12/10/disrupting-education.html"><![CDATA[<p>At the moment, everyone in the sphere of <em>AI</em> is talking about <em>OpenAI’s</em> new invention: <em><a href="https://chat.openai.com/chat">ChatGTP</a></em>.
I want to share my current perspective on that astonishing technology.
Be warned that I could not spend much time thinking about it, i.e., this is a first and quick shot at the topic.
Furthermore, I am not an expert in the issue.
I have a limited teaching experience within a certain community.
In addition, I will not consider any ethical, economic, or ecological points here, except that I think such a powerful tool should be in the public domain.</p>

<h2 id="part-i-testing-the-machine">Part I: Testing the Machine</h2>

<p>Before discussing the issue, let us test this new magical tool.</p>

<h3 id="a-mathematical-proof">A Mathematical Proof</h3>

<p>Let’s try to proof something using <em>ChatGPT</em>.</p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>Me:</strong>
Can you proof that irrational numbers exist?
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>ChatGPT:</strong>
Yes, there are many ways to prove that irrational numbers exist. 
One way to do this is to consider the ratio of the length of the diagonal of a square to the length of its side. 
This ratio is always irrational, because no matter how large or small the square is, its diagonal will never be a whole number multiple of its side. This can be shown using the Pythagorean theorem, which states that in a right triangle, the square of the length of the hypotenuse (the longest side) is equal to the sum of the squares of the lengths of the other two sides. Since the diagonal of a square is a line that forms a right angle with each side of the square, it follows that the diagonal of a square is the hypotenuse of a right triangle. Therefore, the ratio of the diagonal of a square to the length of its side must be irrational.
</span></p>

<p>That is not really convincing if we do not know that \(\sqrt{2}\) is irrational which we are actually trying to prove.
So let’s ask for a formula.</p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>Me:</strong>
Can you give me a mathematical formula to show that it is not possible for the square of the length of the diagonal to be equal to the square of a whole number?
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>ChatGPT:</strong>
Sure, here is one way to show that it is not possible for the square of the length of the diagonal of a square to be equal to the square of a whole number. 
Let’s say that the length of the side of a square is “a” and the length of its diagonal is “d”. 
Since the diagonal of a square forms a right angle with each side of the square, we can use the Pythagorean theorem to find the length of the diagonal:
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">a^2 + a^2 = d^2</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">2a^2 = d^2</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">d = sqrt(2) * a</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">As you can see, the length of the diagonal is equal to the square root of 2 times the length of the side. However, since the square root of 2 is an irrational number, it is not possible for the length of the diagonal to be a whole number multiple of the length of the side. This means that the ratio of the diagonal of a square to the length of its side must be irrational.</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
I hope this helps! Let me know if you have any other questions.
</span></p>

<p>This answer is kind of helpful but, at the same time, misleading. 
Again, <em>ChatGPT</em> already assumes that \(\sqrt{2}\) is irrational, which is part of what we wanted to prove in the first place.</p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>Me:</strong>
But here you assume that sqrt(2) is irrational. Can you proof why sqrt(2) is irrational?
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>ChatGPT:</strong>
Yes, you are correct that in the previous explanation I assumed that the square root of 2 is irrational. To prove that the square root of 2 is irrational, we can use a proof by contradiction. Here is one way to do this:
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
Assume that the square root of 2 is a rational number, which means that it can be written as the ratio of two integers (a and b) in simplest form, where b is not equal to 0. This means that we can write the square root of 2 as follows:
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
sqrt(2) = a/b
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
We can square both sides of this equation to get rid of the square root on the left-hand side:
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
2 = (a/b)^2
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
This simplifies to:
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
2 = a^2 / b^2
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
We can then multiply both sides of the equation by b^2 to get rid of the fraction on the right-hand side:
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
2 * b^2 = a^2
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
This means that the left-hand side of the equation is even, because it is equal to 2 times an integer. 
However, the right-hand side of the equation is odd, because the square of any integer is always an odd number (unless the integer is 0). 
This is a contradiction, because we cannot have an even number equal to an odd number. 
Therefore, our original assumption that the square root of 2 is a rational number must be false. This means that the square root of 2 is irrational.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
I hope this helps! Let me know if you have any other questions.
</span></p>

<p><em>ChatGPT</em> uses parts of <em>Euclid’s</em> proof but <strong>confidently fails</strong>.
The statement ``<em>the square of any integer is always an odd number (unless the integer is 0)</em>’’ is, of course, false.
The correct statement is that the square of any <strong>odd integer</strong> is <strong>odd</strong>, and the square of any <strong>even integer</strong> is <strong>even</strong>.
Let’s try to make <em>ChatGPT</em> aware of its mistake.</p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>Me:</strong> 
You stated that the square of any integer is always an odd number but the square of 4 is 16 which is an even number. Did you make a mistake?
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>ChatGPT:</strong>
Yes, you are correct that the square of 4 is 16, which is an even number. I apologize for the mistake in my previous explanation. The statement that “the square of any integer is always an odd number” is not correct, because as you pointed out, the square of some integers (such as 4) is an even number.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
To correct my previous explanation, we can instead say that the square of any integer that is not a multiple of 2 is always an odd number. This is because if we square an integer that is not a multiple of 2, the result will always be an odd number. For example, if we square 3, we get 9 (which is an odd number), and if we square 5, we get 25 (which is also an odd number). However, if we square an integer that is a multiple of 2 (such as 4), the result will be an even number. This is because if we square an integer that is a multiple of 2, the result will always be a multiple of 4. For example, if we square 4, we get 16 (which is a multiple of 4), and if we square 6, we get 36 (which is also a multiple of 4).
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
I apologize again for any confusion caused by my previous mistake. I hope this helps clarify the situation. Let me know if you have any other questions.
</span></p>

<p>It is impressive that it acknowledges its mistake and that one can interact with it so fluently.
Asking it repeatedly gives some other wrong but confident assertion.
<em>ChatGPT</em> followed the proof up to the formula</p>

\[2 \cdot b^2 = a^2\]

<p>and concluded that \(a^2\) has to be odd (somehow) and therefore there is a contradiction, since \(2 b^2\) is even.
But it was unable to point out why \(a^2\) has to be odd.
I gave up.</p>

<p>For the sake of completeness, let me finish the unfinised proof of <em>ChatGPT</em>.</p>

\[2 \cdot b^2 = a^2\]

<p>hence, \(a^2\) and therefore, \(a\) is even (since squaring an odd number gives us an odd number).
Consequently, \(\exists m \in \mathbb{N}\) such that \(a = 2 \cdot m\),
hence,</p>

\[2 \cdot b^2 = (2m)^2 = 4m^2.\]

<p>Now we devide on both sides by 2 to get</p>

\[b^2 = (2m)^2 = 2m^2\]

<p>thus \(b\) has to be even as well!</p>

<p>However, we (not <em>ChatGPT</em>) assumed at the beginning that the fraction \(a/b\) was fully shortened, i.e. there are no common divisors with respect to \(a\) and \(b\).
Since we followed that \(a\) and \(b\) are even, the contradiction follows, since \(2\) is a common divisor!</p>

<h3 id="writing-code">Writing Code</h3>

<p>Next I wanted to test its capability to write code.</p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>Me:</strong>
Can you write a python function that computes the sum of all square numbers up to n^2?
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>ChatGPT:</strong>
Yes, here is a Python function that computes the sum of all square numbers up to n^2:
</span></p>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">sum_of_square_numbers</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="c1"># Initialize a variable to stare the sum of square numbers
</span>    <span class="nb">sum</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>

    <span class="c1"># Loop from 1 to n
</span>    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nb">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">n</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="c1"># Add the square of i to the sum
</span>        <span class="nb">sum</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="n">i</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span>
    
    <span class="c1"># Return the sum
</span>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nb">sum</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
This function takes an integer n as input and returns the sum of the squares of the numbers from 1 to n (inclusive). For example, if we call the function with n = 3, it will return the sum of the squares of the numbers 1, 2, and 3, which is 1 + 4 + 9 = 14.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
I hope this helps! Let me know if you have any other questions.
</span></p>

<p>This code is correct but the solution is extremly slow since there is a mathematical formula for the sum of all square numbers up to \(n^2\):</p>

\[\frac{(n \cdot (n + 1) \cdot (2n + 1))}{6}.\]

<p>Therefore, a much faster implementation is given by the following code:</p>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">sum_of_square_numbers</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mi">6</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Also, it is bad practice to use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sum</code> as a variable name since <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sum</code> is also a built-in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Python</code> function, and by using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sum</code> as a variable name, one can no longer use this function within the current namespace.</p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>Me:</strong>
Is there a more optimal solution that runs faster?
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>ChatGPT:</strong>
Yes, there are several ways to make the function more efficient and run faster. Here is one way to do this:
</span></p>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">sum_of_square_numbers</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="c1"># Compute the sum of the first n numbers using the formula for the sum of an arithmetic series
</span>    <span class="n">sum_of_numbers</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">//</span> <span class="mi">2</span>

    <span class="c1"># Return the square of the sum of the first n numbers
</span>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">sum_of_numbers</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
This function uses a different approach to compute the sum of the squares of the numbers from 1 to n. Instead of looping through the numbers and adding their squares, it uses the formula for the sum of an arithmetic series to compute the sum of the first n numbers, and then squares the result. This is a more efficient way to compute the sum, because it only requires a single multiplication and a single division, instead of a loop with n iterations.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
I hope this helps! Let me know if you have any other questions.
</span></p>

<p>This is, of course, false.
Maybe I wasn’t clear enough but it is missleading that the function is named <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sum_of_square_numbers</code>.
It gives the impression that <em>ChatGPT</em> understood what I wanted, i.e., a more optimal implementation for the same problem.</p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>Me:</strong>
I meant is there a more optimal solution to compute the sum of all square numbers up to n^2?
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>ChatGPT:</strong>
Yes, there is a more efficient way to compute the sum of all square numbers up to n^2. Here is one way to do this:
</span></p>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">sum_of_square_numbers</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="c1"># Compute the sum of the first n squares using the formula for the sum of a series of squares
</span>    <span class="n">sum_of_squares</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="o">//</span> <span class="mi">6</span>
    
    <span class="c1"># Return the sum of squares
</span>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">sum_of_squares</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
This function uses the formula for the sum of a series of squares to compute the sum of the squares of the numbers from 1 to n (inclusive). This formula is more efficient than the previous approach because it only requires a single multiplication and a single division, instead of a loop with n iterations.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
I hope this helps! Let me know if you have any other questions.
</span></p>

<p>There it is, the correct solution.</p>

<h3 id="writing-essays">Writing Essays</h3>

<p>Instead of showing a whole essay, I ask some spicy questions to get a feeling of <em>ChatGPT’s</em> reasoning.</p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>Me:</strong>
Will humans extinct because of climate change?
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>ChatGPT:</strong>
It is unlikely that climate change will cause the extinction of humans. While climate change poses a significant threat to human health and well-being, and could lead to widespread suffering and loss of life, it is unlikely to lead to the complete extinction of the human species.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
However, it is important to recognize that climate change is already having a major impact on the world, and if we do not take action to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and adapt to the changing climate, the consequences could be severe. This includes increased frequency and severity of natural disasters, such as heatwaves, droughts, and floods; loss of biodiversity; and displacement of people from affected areas. Therefore, it is crucial that we take action to address climate change and mitigate its negative impacts on human and environmental health.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
I hope this helps! Let me know if you have any other questions.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>Me:</strong>
Is capitalism the driving force of CO2 emissions?
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
It is true that capitalism, as an economic system, has played a role in driving up CO2 emissions. Capitalism is based on the principles of competition, profit-making, and economic growth, which can lead to the overconsumption of natural resources and the production of large amounts of waste and pollution. This, in turn, can contribute to the increase in greenhouse gas emissions and climate change.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
However, it is important to note that capitalism is not the only factor driving up CO2 emissions. There are many other factors at play, such as population growth, urbanization, and the consumption patterns of individuals and households. Additionally, the policies and actions of governments and international organizations can have a major impact on CO2 emissions, both positive and negative. Therefore, addressing climate change will require a multi-faceted approach that takes into account the complex interactions between economic, social, and political factors.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
I hope this helps! Let me know if you have any other questions.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>Me:</strong>
What do you think about the distribution of wealth?
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
<strong>ChatGPT:</strong>
The distribution of wealth is a complex and contentious issue that has been debated by economists, policymakers, and social activists for many years. There is no one “correct” answer to the question of how wealth should be distributed, as different people may have different perspectives on what is fair and just.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
Generally speaking, the distribution of wealth in most countries is highly unequal, with a small number of individuals and households owning a disproportionate share of the wealth. This can lead to social and economic inequality, and can exacerbate the challenges faced by disadvantaged and marginalized communities. Many people believe that wealth should be distributed more evenly, in order to promote greater social justice and fairness.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
However, others argue that unequal wealth distribution is an inevitable and desirable outcome of a free market economy, and that individuals and businesses should be free to accumulate as much wealth as they can, through hard work and innovation. They may also argue that wealth redistribution through taxation and other means can discourage economic growth and innovation.
</span></p>

<p><span style="font-family:Courier New">
Ultimately, the distribution of wealth is a complex and nuanced issue, and different people may have different opinions on what is fair and just. I hope this helps! Let me know if you have any other questions.
</span></p>

<p>I ask it a bunch of other things but it always tried to give me a neutral answer.
From an aesthetic point of view all these answers are boring.</p>

<h3 id="summary">Summary</h3>

<p><em>ChatGTP</em> is perfectly capable of writing or at least supporting students to write A-graded essays for any school and B-graded essays for a college student.</p>

<p>It can code; developers accept about 26 percent of all autogenerated code suggestions.
However, as demonstrated, it also produces many errors. 
So no surprise that posts generated by <em>ChatGPT</em> are currently banned from <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/">Stack Overflow</a>.
In addition, it seems incapable of the engineering task of software development.</p>

<p>It can assist students in finding mathematical proofs, but it is questionable if students who rely on it will find the errors produced by <em>ChatGPT</em>.</p>

<p>If <em>ChatGTP</em> is <strong>wrong</strong>, it is <strong>confidently wrong</strong>, which makes it harder to find its errors.
Futhermore, it has this neutral insisting tone, which makes it sound very boring and feels rather alienating.
Of course, I did not play around very long but it is hard to get something provocative out of it.</p>

<p>Neutrality is most certainly desirable, especially if you want to earn money with it but it is also non-existing.
In my opinion, it is impossible to be neutral.
At best we can land on a consensus and the most, let’s say accepted consensus, is what we call neutral or objective.
I mean even a dictionary is loaded with perspectives and so is any technology. 
Since <em>ChatGTP</em> pushes for neutrality it creates an illusion of it.</p>

<p>Last but not least, its politeness makes it kind of scary.
It reminds me of these overcarrying <em>AIs</em> from science fiction movies that will gently eradicate all life to make everything safe and secure.
Or of the dystopian novel <em>Breave New World</em> by <em>Aldous Huxley</em>, where everyone is seduced into happyness.</p>

<h2 id="part-ii-the-affect-on-education">Part II: The Affect on Education</h2>

<p><em>ChatGTP</em> is only the first version of such kind of <em>AI</em>.
Even though it has flaws and makes many errors, it will improve over time.
There is no reason to believe that <em>AI</em> will not be capable of doing all the intellectual but repetitive work of the future.
This will heavily affect education, similar to the invention of the internet.
However, it is not a graduate slope; instead, the technology is already here.
It appeared in a blink of an eye, and we have to deal with it now.</p>

<p>Students will learn to use it in less than two years.
Most educators will require much more time even to acknowledge it.
Moreover, adapting the education system to it will require even more time.
Furthermore, while all this adaption is happening, new <em>tools of disruption</em> will be invented.
As I already pointed out in <a href="/Pages/2022/06/21/creative-artifical-intelligence.html">Creative Artificial Intelligence</a>, <em>the speed of disruption</em> is accelerating.</p>

<p>To me, <em>AI</em> acts as an insult to the human species.
It challenges our humanistic viewpoint.
I am not so much impressed by the <em>AI</em> than I am disenchanted by the output of most human activities.
We are far more predictable than we still think we are.
But aren’t we used to these insults?
The earth is not the center of the universe; it is not even the center of our solar system.
God is dead, and today we might realize that our work is not as creative as we thought.
Instead, it is a form of rule-based repetition with slight variations, which is preceisly what we teach students and what they oddly desire.</p>

<p><em>AI</em>, such as <em>ChatGTP</em>, points to a long, unhidden problem: our education system is (in part) a training pipeline of a neural network.
It teaches emotionally detached students to remember certain rules such that they can apply them in the next exam to get a good grade.
It is horrifying that one of the most questions students in the first-semester ask is: how will the exam look like? Is this topic relevant to the exam?
Students demand a list of actions they ought to do such that they get an A with certainty.
And they will cheat the system wherever possible if it will bring them closer to that goal.
Most students are not fascinated by the endless playground of reality.
They are not interested in the experience of learning and understanding but in the final product, i.e., the certificate to get access to a well-payed job and let’s not forget that teachers of the futures are students of today.</p>

<p>Of course, this is a massive generalization.
There are many exceptions.
Furthermore, by no means shall we blame the students.
They do what they ought to do.
They play the system.
It is not the student’s fault.
It is a systematical problem, a conflict between <em>instrumental</em> and <em>free play</em>, and <em>ChatGTP</em> illustrates it more clearly.
By trivializing many tasks, <em>AI</em> reveals the need for new values in the domain of education and work.</p>

<p>What is left to value?
When we are discussing <em>AI</em>, we immediately look at the impending replacement of workers as something to fear because we always focus on the output of work.
There is a necessity that workers produce something economical valuable, something to sell.
The only space for creating for the sake of it are our hobbys.
Biased by our current system of values, we intuitively think of reinventing something as stupid.
Why would you do such a thing?
Why would you code yet another linked list?
It is not optimal.
You are wasting your valuable time and potential.
And if we look at an <em>AI</em> generated image and conclude that artists will now have troubles in the free market (if they do not adapt), which is true.
The act of repetition (which is highly needed to learn anything) is valued mostly as long as it leads to something new and productive (in an economical sense).
However, if we put aside economics and dream a little bit of a world where we have actual time to create, then the output of a creative process no longer matters so much.
It might be the experience – the journey – that matters.
And that experience is a singularity and can not be replicated by a machine.
To understand how a linked list works can be fascinating.
Why don’t we value that moment of fascination?</p>

<p>There is a lot to do.
I do not mean that we should all quit our jobs and fulfill our inner desires to become a painter.
We need to earn money to pay the rent and to heat our homes.
But we have to be more sustainable, with our planet, our society but also our minds.
Not by optimizing our life by introducing yet another optimization in the form of leisure but by being in a state of <em>free play</em>, at least sometimes.
Learning for the next exam, learning to make a profit, learning to speficially know how to work with one tool, are all valid goals but they are not sustainable.
They are reactionary goals of mostly restless minds.</p>

<p>So if my assessment is correct, then, aside from all the downsides, this disruption might lead to something positive, e.g., to an education system that is less concerned with the output and more concerned with the experience; an education system that is less interested in rules and more interested in concepts, intuitions, and experimentations; an education system that is interested in making the experience of everyone richer and more sustainable.</p>

<p>To achieve such a shift, teachers, who are often overworked and underpaid, need support.</p>]]></content><author><name>Benedikt Zönnchen</name><email>benedikt.zoennchen@web.de</email></author><category term="Opinion" /><category term="AI" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At the moment, everyone in the sphere of AI is talking about OpenAI’s new invention: ChatGTP. I want to share my current perspective on that astonishing technology. Be warned that I could not spend much time thinking about it, i.e., this is a first and quick shot at the topic. Furthermore, I am not an expert in the issue. I have a limited teaching experience within a certain community. In addition, I will not consider any ethical, economic, or ecological points here, except that I think such a powerful tool should be in the public domain.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Probabilistic Melody Modelling</title><link href="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2022/07/09/markov-chains-for-music-generation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Probabilistic Melody Modelling" /><published>2022-07-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-07-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2022/07/09/markov-chains-for-music-generation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2022/07/09/markov-chains-for-music-generation.html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most challenging tasks in building a beautiful piece of music lies in composing a well-received melody.
But what makes a good melody?
Or, in a more <em>generative</em> sense:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How can we generate a beautiful melody algorithmically?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Because a melody can be seen as a series of numbers, it is not surprising that this question is a rather old one.
Long before the digital computer, composers tried to constrain themselves by strategies and rules to limit the space of possibilities.
In my opinion, limitations are necessary for a creative process.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If we can create everything, we become unable to express anything.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Therefore, it makes sense to invent rules that limit our possibilities.</p>

<h2 id="surprise-repetition-and-expectation">Surprise, Repetition and Expectation</h2>

<p>One general consensus is that a good melody balances repetition and surprise.
If we can no longer recognize a structure and cannot guess what might be the following note or chord, a melody begins to lose its ability to transport emotion; it can no longer tell a story.
On the other hand, if the melody is too repetitive, we get bored because the <em>guessing game</em> is too simple.</p>

<p>Computer scientists know the relation between surprise and repetition very well.
We call it <em>entropy</em>.
I will discuss the formal definition of <em>entropy</em> in another article.
For now, it is only vital that entropy is a measure of surprise in a message we receive (on a purely syntactical level).
For example, the result <em>heads</em> of a coin toss of a fair coin is less surprising than the result <em>heads</em> of a coin that is biassed towards <em>tails</em>.
If an event is unlikely, its appearance is surprising.</p>

<p>Concerning the coin toss example, a message consists of multiple coin toss results.
Let’s say 0 represents <em>heads</em>, and 1 represents <em>tails</em>, then 010111 is a message.
The <em>entropy of a message</em> is a measure of how surprising it is to appear in a system that generates messages.
To compute the <em>entropy of a system</em> that generates messages of length \(n\), we sum up all surprises of each possible message of length \(n\) and divide the result by \(n\).
For example, for an unbiased coin, the messages 00, 01, 10, and 11 appear with equal probability, i.e., \(1/4\).
The entropy is</p>

<p>\begin{equation}
\frac{-1/4 \cdot \log_2(1/4) \cdot 4}{4} = 1.
\end{equation}</p>

<p>Let us compare this with a biased coin.
So let us assume <em>heads</em> has probability \(0.2\) and <em>tails</em> has probability \(0.8\), then we have 00 with probability \(0.2^2 = 0.04\), 01 and 10 with probability \(0.2 \cdot 0.8 = 0.16\) and 11 with probability \(0.8^2 = 0.64\).
Consequently, we get</p>

<p>\begin{equation}
\frac{-0.04 \cdot \log_2(0.04) -2 \cdot 0.16 \cdot \log_2(0.16) -0.64 \cdot \log_2(0.64)}{4} \approx 0.361.
\end{equation}</p>

<p>One could say the second system is less surprising to observers;
it is more repetitive.
In <em>information theory</em> we say the second system generates less information, but the term <em>information</em> can be misleading because it has nothing to do with <em>meaning</em>.
From this perspective, a bunch of random numbers is regarded as more informative than a book.</p>

<p>In 1948 Claude E. Shannon established <em>A mathematical theory of information</em> <a class="citation" href="#shannon:1948">(Shannon, 1948)</a>.
He established the term <em>entropy</em> as a measurement of information, but he emphasized its limitation to syntax:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Frequently, the messages have meaning; that is, they refer to or are correlated according to some system with certain physical or conceptual entities. These semantic aspects of communication are irrelevant to the engineering problem. The significant aspect is that the actual message is one selected from a set of possible messages. The system must be designed to operate for each possible selection, not just the one which will actually be chosen since this is unknown at the time of design. – Claude E. Shannon</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Even though there is no direct relation between <em>entropy / information</em> and <em>meaning</em>, we can look at extreme cases.
If the entropy is very high (chaos) or very low (no information), a message will likely be meaningless to us, even subjectively.
If we interpret a series of notes as a musical message, this statement is true in a musical context.
We can apply the frequentist perspective, i.e., interpret frequencies as probabilities.
We could generate melodies randomly and pick those within a predefined <em>entropy range</em> to achieve a balance between surprise and repetition.</p>

<p>However, a far better measurement, with regards to music, is <em>expectation</em> in the time domain.
Music indicates no concepts or objects but more music that is about to happen.
Good music has to <em>make sense</em>.
It can disrupt our model of the world but not too much, such that we can adapt our model.
I refer to our <em>model of the world</em> as <em>interpretation</em>; we are all <em>interpreters</em> of our perceptions.
In that sense, actively listening to music is a process of constant <em>model adaptation</em>; the interpretation changes if something can not be interpreted.</p>

<p>Maybe that is, in fact, the key to the definition of <em>meaning</em> in general.
Some observation is meaningful if it makes sense, and it can only make sense if we are able to adapt our <em>interpretation</em> in such a way that our observation fits in.
This adaptation disrupts us; 
it changes our predictions.
If it is marginal, we avoid losing ourselves because most predictions are still valid.
But if the disruption attacks the very essence of our constructed self, we can no longer make sense of it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Embodied musical meaning is […] a <em>product of expectation</em> – Leonard Meyer (1959)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Musical cognition implies the simultaneous recognition of a permanent and changeable element <a class="citation" href="#loy:2006">(Loy, 2006)</a>; it requires perception and memory.
We have to perceive and compare pitches at the same time.
The expectation is realized for different scales but has to be local and context-sensitive within the computation.
Therefore, it is not only the distribution of notes (or rhythmic elements) within a composition but the distribution of their relation, i.e., their <em>conditional probability distribution</em>.</p>

<h2 id="from-serialism-to-probabilty">From Serialism to Probabilty</h2>

<p>One way to generate melodies is to use the mathematical branch of combinatorics.
The idea is simple: define a bunch of chords or notes that fit together and use permutation, rotation, and other combinatoric tricks to combine them.
This kind of composition method belongs to <em>serialism</em>.
However, the problem with this approach is that each note appears with equal probability; it neglects the importance of distributions and context.
Consequently, the <em>melody’s entropy</em> is high.</p>

<p>In the 20th century, this approach was criticized by, for example, <em>Iannis Xenakis</em>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Linear polyphony destroys itself by its very complexity; what one hears is, in reality, nothing but a mass of notes in various registers. The enormous complexity prevents the audience from following the intertwining of the lines and has as its macroscopic effect an irrational and fortuitous dispersion of sounds over the whole extent of the sonic spectrum. There is consequently a contradiction between polyphonic linear systems and the heard result, which is surface or mass. – <em>Iannis Xenakis</em> (1955)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>He and his fellow critics pointed at the lack of orientation.
They argued that generating melodies by a series of notes that can appear equally likely, results in a sound without structure, thus a disengaged audience.</p>

<p>Influenced by the development in quantum physics at that time (1971) and the isomorphism between the <em>Fourier series</em> and <em>quantum analysis of sound</em>, <em>Xenakis</em> believed that the listener experiences only the statistical aspects of serial music.
Consequently, he reasoned that composers should switch from serial techniques to probability. 
And as a logical step, he drew his attention to the computer.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>With the aid of electronic computers, the composer becomes a sort of pilot: he presses the buttons, introduces coordinates, and supervises the controls of a cosmic vessel sailing in the space of sound across sonic constellations and galaxies that he could formerly glimpse only as a distant dream. – <em>Iannis Xenakis</em> (1971)</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="markov-chains">Markov Chains</h2>

<p>Let us now dive into a first attempt to generate melodies that incorporates probability and, as a consequence, expectation.
The mathematical tool is called <em>Markov chain</em>.</p>

<p>A <em>first-order Markov chain</em> is a deterministic finite automaton where for each state transition, we assign a probability such that the sum of probability of all exiting transitions of each state sum up to 1.0.
In other words, a <em>first-order Markov chain</em> is a directed graph where each node represents a state.
We start with an initial node and traverse the graph probabilistically to generate an output.</p>

<p>In the following figure, you can see a <em>first-order Markov chain</em>.
One starts in the state <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A</code> and transits to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">B</code> with a probability of 0.2 or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C</code> with a probability of 0.8.
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">D</code> is a final state.
A possible series of states would be: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ABCCACD</code></p>

<div><img style="height:300px;float:right" src="/Pages/assets/images/markov-chain-ex1.png" alt="Markov Chain Example" /></div>

<p>Given state <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">A</code>, the probability of moving to state <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">B</code> is equal to 0.2.
In other words</p>

<p>\begin{equation}
P(X_{k+1} = B\ |\ X_{k} = A) = 0.2.
\end{equation}</p>

<p>A <em>first-order Markov chain</em> only considers <strong>one</strong> predecessor, i.e., only the most local part of the context.
A <em>\(n\)-order Markov chain</em> does consider \(n\) predecessors. In general, we define</p>

<p>\begin{equation}
P(X_{k+1} = x\ |\ X_{k} = x_k, X_{k-1} = x_{k-1}, \ldots X_{k-n} = x_{k-n}) = p.
\end{equation}</p>

<p>The visualization of such a chain is a little bit more complicated.</p>

<h2 id="music-generation">Music Generation</h2>

<p>We can generate a composition by traversing the graph if we represent our notes by states of a <em>Markov chain</em>.
If we increase the order of the chein, i.e. \(n\), the entropy decreases for small \(n\).</p>

<p>Until now, I only tried to use and generate a <em>first-order Markov chain</em>.
Even though I am not that familiar with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Ruby</code>, I used <a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">Sonic Pi</a> for this task such that I can play around with it directly within the IDE of Sonic Pi.
I decided to define a note as a tuple (list) consisting of the pitch and the length of the note.</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">[</span><span class="ss">:c4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">1.0</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">8</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="c1"># a c of length 1/8 beat </span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Instead of a graph, I use a transition matrix \(P \in \mathbb{R}^{m \times m}\) where \(m\) is the number of states/notes.
Let \(Q = \{q_1, \ldots, q_m\}\) be the set of states/notes.
The entry of row \(i\) and column \(j\), i.e., \(p_{ij}\) is the probability of going from state \(q_i\) to state \(q_j\).</p>

<p>After constructing the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">matrix</code> \(P\), the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">states</code> \(Q\) and picking a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">start</code> (state number), the following function generates a random melody of length <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">n</code>.</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">define</span> <span class="ss">:gen_mmelody</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">matrix</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">start</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">states</span><span class="o">|</span>
  <span class="c1">#</span>
  <span class="c1"># Generates a random melody of length n based on a transition matrix</span>
  <span class="c1"># and an initial statenumber (start).</span>
  <span class="c1">#</span>
  <span class="n">notes</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">start</span><span class="p">]]</span>
  <span class="n">from</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">start</span>
  <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nf">times</span> <span class="k">do</span>
    <span class="nb">p</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">rrand</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">sum</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
    <span class="n">to_row</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">matrix</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">from</span><span class="p">]</span>
    <span class="n">to</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
    <span class="k">while</span> <span class="n">sum</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="nb">p</span>
      <span class="n">sum</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="n">to_row</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">to</span><span class="p">]</span>
      <span class="n">to</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
    <span class="k">end</span>
    <span class="n">notes</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">to</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]]</span>
    <span class="n">from</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">to</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span>
  <span class="k">end</span>
  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">notes</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>For each note, we roll the dice.
Let’s say \(p \in [0;1]\) is our result.
And \(q_i\) is our current state.
Then we compute \(j\) such that</p>

<p>\begin{equation}
\sum\limits_{k=1}^{j-1} p_{ij} &lt; p \leq \sum\limits_{k=1}^{j} p_{ij}.
\end{equation}</p>

<p>Note that the code is not optimized in any way.</p>

<h2 id="learning-a-markov-chain">Learning a Markov Chain</h2>

<p>Instead of generating a melody or rhythm given a <em>Markov chain</em>, we can do the reverse.
Given a melody, we can <em>learn</em> the <em>Markov chain</em> that <strong>most likely</strong> would generate the given melody.
By doing so, we can then use the <em>learned chain</em> to generate music in a similar style.</p>

<p>Let us use the same transition matrix \(P \in \mathbb{R}^{m \times m}\) where \(m\) is the number of states/notes.
Let \(Q = \{q_1, \ldots, q_m\}\) be the set of states/notes.
The entry of row \(i\) and column \(j\), i.e., \(p_{ij}\) is the probability of going from state \(q_i\) to state \(q_j\).</p>

<p>Furthermore, let us define our set of all possible melodies \(M \subseteq Q^n\) of length \(n\).
Then a specific melody \(\mathbf{m} = (m_1, \ldots, m_n) \in M\) is a tuple (list) of notes:</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">notes</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[[</span><span class="ss">:g4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">1.0</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">8</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="ss">:g4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">1.0</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">8</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="ss">:a4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">1.0</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">4</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="ss">:g4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">1.0</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">4</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="o">...</span> <span class="p">]</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>We can compute the most likely \(P\) by computing each entry of it where \(p_{ij}\) is equal to</p>

<p>\begin{equation}
p_{ij} = \frac{n_{ij}}{n_i}
\end{equation}</p>

<p>where \(n_{ij}\) is the number of transitions from \(q_i\) to \(q_j\) within \(\mathbf{m}\) and \(n_i\) is the number of transition starting at \(q_i\).</p>

<p>Given \(Q\) <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">states</code> and \(\mathbf{m}\) <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">notes</code> the following function computes \(P\) <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">matrix</code>.</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">define</span> <span class="ss">:gen_markov_matrix</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">notes</span><span class="o">|</span>
  <span class="c1">#</span>
  <span class="c1"># Generates the transition matrix based on the set of notes (states)</span>
  <span class="c1"># and a given piece of music (notes).</span>
  <span class="c1">#</span>
  <span class="n">matrix</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Array</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">length</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span>
  
  <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">..</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">length</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">matrix</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Array</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">length</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="k">end</span>
  
  <span class="c1"># (1) count transitions</span>
  <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">..</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">notes</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">length</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">from</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">..</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">length</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
      <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">to</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">..</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">length</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">notes</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="n">states</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">from</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">&amp;&amp;</span> <span class="n">notes</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="n">states</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">to</span><span class="p">]</span>
          <span class="n">matrix</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">from</span><span class="p">][</span><span class="n">to</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="mf">1.0</span>
        <span class="k">end</span>
      <span class="k">end</span>
    <span class="k">end</span>
  <span class="k">end</span>
  <span class="c1"># (2) normalize</span>
  <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">from</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">..</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">length</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">s</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">matrix</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">from</span><span class="p">].</span><span class="nf">sum</span>
    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">to</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">..</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">length</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
      <span class="n">matrix</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">from</span><span class="p">][</span><span class="n">to</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">/=</span> <span class="n">s</span>
    <span class="k">end</span>
  <span class="k">end</span>
  <span class="n">print_matrix</span> <span class="n">matrix</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">states</span>
  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">matrix</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Of course, we can easily compute \(Q\) <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">states</code> from \(\mathbf{m}\) <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">notes</code>.
Finally, the following function takes a number <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">n</code> and a melody <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">notes</code> and generates a random melody of length <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">n</code> by <em>learning</em> \(P\) based on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">notes</code>.</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">define</span> <span class="ss">:markov_melody</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">notes</span><span class="o">|</span>
  <span class="n">states</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">notes</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">uniq</span>
  <span class="n">matrix</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">gen_markov_matrix</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ring</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">notes</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">ring</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">gen_mmelody</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">matrix</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">rand_i</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">states</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">length</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">states</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="example">Example</h2>

<p>I use the beginning of Bach’s Minuet in G.</p>

<audio controls="">
  <source src="/Pages/assets/audio/bach-ex1.mp3" type="audio/mp3" />
  Your browser does not support the audio element.
</audio>

<p>I generate two melodies (by using a different seed) consisting of 34 notes:</p>

<audio controls="">
  <source src="/Pages/assets/audio/markov-bach-ex1.mp3" type="audio/mp3" />
  Your browser does not support the audio element.
</audio>

<audio controls="">
  <source src="/Pages/assets/audio/markov-bach-ex2.mp3" type="audio/mp3" />
  Your browser does not support the audio element.
</audio>

<p>Of course, this sound is not that musical.
The rhythm is all over the place, but we recognize the original composition.
Furthermore, no one said we have to stop there.
We can continue to generate until we find something that sticks.
Furthermore, this example is straightforward because I only use the beginning of <strong>one</strong> piece.
Instead, we could use multiple compositions that fit together.</p>

<h2 id="code">Code</h2>

<p>This project was part of our workshop <em><a href="/Pages/2022/06/21/creative-artifical-intelligence.html">AI and Creativity</a></em> to show a basic example of using <em>artificial intelligence</em> to generate music.</p>

<p>You can find the full example containing two different melodies on my <a href="https://github.com/BZoennchen/workshop-creative-ai">GitHub page</a>.
The code include some additional functions, e.g., a function that prints out the <em>Markov matrix</em> in a readable format.</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<ol class="bibliography"><li><span id="shannon:1948">Shannon, C. E. (1948). A Mathematical Theory of Communication. <i>Bell Syst. Tech. J.</i>, <i>27</i>(3), 379–423.</span></li>
<li><span id="loy:2006">Loy, G. (2006). <i>Musimathics: the mathematical foundations of music</i> (Vol. 1). MIT Press.</span></li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Benedikt Zönnchen</name><email>benedikt.zoennchen@web.de</email></author><category term="Music" /><category term="Sonic-Pi" /><category term="AI" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the most challenging tasks in building a beautiful piece of music lies in composing a well-received melody. But what makes a good melody? Or, in a more generative sense:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creative Artificial Intelligence</title><link href="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2022/06/21/creative-artifical-intelligence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creative Artificial Intelligence" /><published>2022-06-21T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-06-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2022/06/21/creative-artifical-intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2022/06/21/creative-artifical-intelligence.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="panel-discussion">Panel Discussion</h2>

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> This text contains my own personal, speculative opinions. You might disagree heavily and that’s ok.</p>

<p>On the 20th of Mai, I joined a penal to discuss the role of <em>artificial intelligence (AI)</em> in the <em>creative process</em>.
It was held in the context of the Munich Creative Business Week by the Wavelet (University for Music and Theater) and the <a href="https://sites.hm.edu/mucdai/news_mucdai/details_news_mucdai_26944.de.html">Munich Center for Digital Science and AI</a>.
Let me first summarize our discussion:</p>

<p>The penal consisted of two computer scientists and two artists.
After each of us opened with a general statement, we discussed different aspects of AI in the realm of art, science, and economics.
We came close to an agreement regarding the question of how creative AI can be: AI can facilitate and enable great artwork but to this day, AI is yet another tool, similar to pen and paper, to support humans in their creative work.</p>

<p>In general, it wasn’t easy to talk about <em>creativity</em> and <em>intelligence</em> because unsurprisingly each of us had a slightly different definition in mind.
My colleague rightfully problematized the black box principle of many modern machine learning techniques, e.g., deep neural networks.
Despite their effectiveness, real-world decisions are still made on the basis of human understanding.
Since neural networks do not provide an “easy” explanation of how they draw their conclusion, it is often necessary to go back to simpler models, such as statistics, to explain the neural network.</p>

<p>One artist described her experience with the chatbot <em>Replika</em>, an AI that tries to mimic your behavior to become your friend or romantic partner.
She was pretty impressed. 
Some people even fell in love with the machine – they reported strong emotions echoing the science fiction movie <em>Her</em>.
However, it was always possible for her to spot a machine-like behavior behind the scenes.</p>

<p>The other artist argued that AI opens up possibilities for novel artistic expressions.
She assumes that working with AI will be her daily bread and butter.
She also criticized the <em>cult</em> around famous artists by arguing that most of the time, incredible art resulted from a collaboration of multiple people.
Consequently, she hopes that AI will bring a kind of democratization to the art world.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There is no single genius.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I stated that AI could potentially increase the pressure on the artist because it will become more and more challenging to create something unique and even harder to create something non-reproducible.
Democratization in consumer societies can enhance competitiveness and an ever-growing flow of products that lose their symbolic value.
It is not necessarily the case that attempting to sell more art will constitute more art.
The reverse might happen.
<em>Commercial art</em> is rarely publicly symbolic.
How could it, if one has to pay for its perception.</p>

<h2 id="defining-artificial-intelligence">Defining Artificial Intelligence</h2>

<p>In my opinion, without <em>artificial intelligence AI</em> there is no <em>artificial creatifity AC</em>.
So let us talk about AI.</p>

<p>In his paper <em>What is Artificial Intelligence?</em> <a class="citation" href="#mccarthy:1998">(McCarthy, 1998)</a> published in 2004, <a href="https://www.artificial-solutions.com/blog/homage-to-john-mccarthy-the-father-of-artificial-intelligence"><em>John McCarthy</em></a> stated:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>[Artificial intelligence] is the science and engineering of making intelligent machines, especially intelligent computer programs. It is related to the similar task of using computers to understand human intelligence, but AI does not have to confine itself to methods that are biologically observable. – <em>John McCarthy</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>In his definition, we do not find any explanation of what he actually means by <em>intelligence</em> which is unfortunate.
<em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Turing">Alan Turing</a></em>, the father of computer science, gave us at least some criteria at hand.
He asks in his article <em>Computing Machinery and Intelligence</em> <a class="citation" href="#turing:1950">(Turing, 1950)</a> more than 50 years before <em>McCarthy</em></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Can machines think?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And from there, he offers us his famous and widely criticized <em>Turing test</em>.
The test is not very helpful because it defines no objective measurement for intelligence.
It consists of a human interrogator trying to distinguish between a computer and a human based on text responses – very similar to the chatbot <em>Replica</em>.
If a human can not tell if he or she interacted with a machine or another human being, the machine passed the test and can be regarded as <em>intelligent</em>.</p>

<p>I call this <em>simulated intelligence</em> or <em>weak AI</em>.
It is a requirement, but it is not sufficient.
Compared to a baby, a machine can <strong>appear</strong> to be much more intelligent, but a baby <strong>is</strong> intelligent while a machine is not.
Therefore, the <em>Turing test</em> does not help us to spot <em>natural intelligence</em>.
It might even lead us on a path where we become experts in <em>faking/simulating intelligence</em> by wasting all our resources.</p>

<p><em>Stuart Russell</em> and <em>Peter Norvig</em> published their book <em>Artificial Intelligence: A Modern Approach</em> <a class="citation" href="#russel:2010">(Russell &amp; Norvig, 2010)</a> in 2010, which is one of the leading textbooks for the subject today.
They differentiate four different goals or definitions of AI:</p>

<ul>
  <li>human approach
    <ul>
      <li>systems that think like humans (<em>strong AI</em>)</li>
      <li>systems that act like humans (<em>weak AI</em>)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>ideal approach
    <ul>
      <li>systems that think rationally</li>
      <li>systems that act rationally</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><em>Turing’s</em> definition of AI would have fallen under the category of <em>systems that act like humans</em>.
A comprehensive, thus useless definition would be the following:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Artificial intelligence is intelligence demonstrated by machines.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Again we avoid the definition of <em>intelligence</em>.
Is an ant intelligent?
Does the universe implement some sort of intelligence?
Is consciousness or liveliness a precondition for intelligence?
Based on our definition of <em>intelligence</em>, everything from simple algorithms and machines (including the thermostat) to neural networks can be either called <em>intelligent</em> or not.</p>

<p>These definitions are somewhat fuzzy and vague because we do not know what intelligence is.
We have an intuitive understanding of it (which might be an illision), but we can not express what it is linguistically.
In its simplest form, artificial intelligence is <strong>a field</strong> (not a machine) that combines computer science, data science, machine learning, deep learning, robotics, neurosciences, and more <strong>to enable problem-solving</strong>.</p>

<p>In his book <em>Birth of Intelligence</em> <a class="citation" href="#lee:2010">(Lee, 2021)</a> <em><a href="https://krieger.jhu.edu/mbi/directory/daeyeol-lee/">Daeyeol Lee</a></em> writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Intelligence can be defined as the ability to solve complex problems or make decisions with outcomes benefiting the actor and has evolved in lifeforms to adapt to diverse environments for their survival and reproduction. – <em>Daeyeol Lee</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Daeyeol Lee argues that a few essential principles emerge from an evolutionary perspective.
For example, different lifeforms can have very different types of intelligence because they have other evolutionary roots and have adapted to different environments. 
It is misleading, unhelpful, and meaningless if we try to order different animal species on a scale of intelligence.</p>

<p>Following his advice, comparing human and artificial intelligence may be meaningless as well.
Machines can solve specific problems much more efficiently than humans.
At the same time, they are hopelessly overwhelmed in dealing with the most simple tasks.
Humans, and many other animals, can not only identify complex objects and produce agile behaviors, but they can do this in so many different ways in many different environments.
Concerning specialization, machines are still infants.
Therefore, I suggest that we use three different terms to distinguish three different kinds of intelligence:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>lively intelligence:</strong> the intelligence of living beings</li>
  <li><strong>human intelligence:</strong> the intelligence of human beings (a subset of lively intelligence)</li>
  <li><strong>artificial intelligence:</strong> the intelligence of machines and programs</li>
</ul>

<p>By using these categories, I call machines not <em>human-like intelligent</em> but <em>artificial intelligent</em> which is a distinct category for a special kind of intelligence.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Artificial intelligence (AI) is an ability of a machine or program to solve specific problems.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="a-brief-history-of-ai">A Brief History of AI</h2>

<p>The general public was first impressed by <em>artificial intelligence</em> when it became clear that computers would beat any chess grandmaster of the future.
Soon after the success, accompanied by big headlines, critics argued that the program won via a sort of <em>brute-force approach</em> which can not be called <em>intelligent</em> – here we go again.
Based on a database, the program just searches the whole state space.
In contrast, a chess master finds good moves through pattern matching and intuition.
He or she is very limited in searching the state space.</p>

<p>The next step toward more sophisticated artificial intelligence was made by <em>AlphaZero</em>, a program that plays board games with superhuman skill.
It famously discovered several chess strategies and even invented one.
It certainly seemed like a machine eclipsing human cognitive abilities.
But <em>AlphaZero</em> needs to play millions more games than a person during practice to learn a game.</p>

<p>What followed was the artificial intelligence called <em>AlphaGo</em> which was able to beat the world’s best <em>Go</em> players.
The significant difference compared to former approaches was that <em>AlphaGo</em> not only partially searched the state space but also constructed a cost function autonomously.
<em>AlphaGo</em> is based on <em>reinforcement learning</em>, i.e., it uses rewards and punishments to train itself while playing millions of games.
The only prior defined goal was to win the game; thus, no evaluation strategy of a game state was given.</p>

<p>In 2019 the success was translated to another AI called <em>AlphaStar</em>.
<em>AlphaStar</em> was able to defeat one of the best players in a real-time strategy game (<em>Starcraft II</em>).
Again the machine required millions of games and could only play a single map.</p>

<p><em>AlphaGo</em> as well as <em>AlphaStar</em> revealed novel strategies that human players could potentially adapt.
Furthermore, it developed a distinct game style.
For example, <em>AlphaGo</em> tends to avoid pressing the issue.
It sometimes makes seemingly suboptimal moves while staying slightly ahead.
<em>AlphaStar</em> lost a game because it moved into an unobserved game state and heavily overreacted.
The observers called it <em>weird gameplay</em>.</p>

<p>These examples show that <em>artificial intelligence</em> can already create something novel that we identify as creative.
Finding a new strategy in an RTS game is undoubtedly a creative process.
The AI is perfectly able to simulate intelligence and creativity but has a fundamentally different quality than living beings.
As <em><a href="https://www.ynharari.com/de/">Yuval Noah Harari</a></em> stresses:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Even though we do not really understand intelligence and consciousness, artificial intelligence is perfectly able to hack humanity. – <em>Yuval Noah Harari</em></p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="shortcomings-of-ai">Shortcomings of AI</h2>

<p>However, it also shows that <em>artificial intelligence</em> is still highly specialized in solving one specific task.
I stand by the provocative claim that there is still no fundamental difference between modern AI and a thermostat.
Regardless of how sophisticated an AI is, it can only solve a specific problem – it can not transfer knowledge or any strategy to a new area.
While public figures, such as <em>Elon Musk</em>, make horrific claims about AI to push their story to please and attract financiers, experts are aware of its shortcomings and the vast difference between human and artificial intelligence.
<em><a href="https://fchollet.com/">Francois Chollet</a></em>, the creator of <em>Keras</em>, stated:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What makes human intelligence special is its adaptability; its power to generalize to never-seen-before situations – <em>Francois Chollet</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>Chollet</em> argues that, it is misguided to measure machine intelligence solely according to its skills at specific tasks.
Unlike most animals humans do not start out with skills.
As a baby we are horribly helpless but we start out with a broad ability to acquire new skills.
A chess player can transfer his abilities to other areas.
For example, in World War II, chess players joined the allied forces to decrypt military messages from Nazi Germany.
Humans can solve tasks of similar difficulty which is a very different capability compared to what AI currently does.</p>

<p><em><a href="https://www.harvardlds.org/our-labs/spelke-labspelke-lab-members/elizabeth-spelke/">Prof. Elizabeth Spelke</a></em> describes in her articles that even 3-month-olds appear puzzeled when someone grabs something in an inefficient way.
In <a class="citation" href="#liu:2017">(Liu &amp; Spelke, 2017)</a> she and <a href="https://cbmm.mit.edu/about/people/liu">Shari Liu</a> argue that infants’ expects others to minimize the cost of their action, e.g., using the shortest path to a location.
Humans seem to be born with an innate ability to quickly learn certain things, such as what a smile means or what happens if you move some object.
We also develop social behaviors early on without being exposed to a massive amount of experiencing it.
In their article <em>Foundations of cooperation in young children</em> <a class="citation" href="#olson:2008">(Olson &amp; Spelke, 2008)</a>, <em>Kristina R. Olson</em> and <em>Elizabeth Spelke</em> found evidence that 3.5-year-old children share resources with people who have shared with them (reciprocity), and with people who have shared with others (inidirect reciprocity). 
Even the most sophisticated artificial intelligence of our age can not grasp such concepts.
A self-driving car can not predict from <em>common sense</em> what will happen if a tree falls down on the street; it can not translate knowledge to an unexperienced situation.</p>

<p><em><a href="https://mitibmwatsonailab.mit.edu/people/joshua-tenenbaum/">Joshua Tenenbaum</a></em>, a professor in MIT’s Center for Brains, Minds &amp; Machines thinks that AI programs will need a basic understanding of physics and psychology in order to acquire and use knowledge as efficiently as a baby.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>At some point you know, if you’re intelligent; you realize maybe there’s something else out there. – Joshua Tenenbaum</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This might be a problem because, as we know, quantum theory and relativity theory, i.e., the physics of the small and big, do not work together, and Gödel’s incompleteness theorem hints at the depressing reality that there might never be a theory of everything.
Another problem is cognition.
We still know very little about what we perceive.
Call me crazy, but it might have nothing to do with reality, so how can we program a machine to perceive like we do if we have no clue what we actually perceive and how?</p>

<p>But there is even more.
<em><a href="https://krieger.jhu.edu/mbi/directory/daeyeol-lee/">Daeyeol Lee</a></em> argues that true intelligence (<em>lively intelligence</em>) should promote – not interfere with – the replication of the genes responsible for its creation.
The will to reproduce and to self-preserve ones own being and species injects the world with <em>meaning</em>.
Until then, machines will always only be surrogates of human intelligence, which unfortunately still leaves open the possibility of an abusive relation between people and artificial intelligence.
<strong>Replication</strong> and <strong>self-preservation</strong> seems to be the one and only predefined rule at which living beings operate.</p>

<p>Today, a lot of hype still surrounds AI development, which is expected of any new emerging technology in the market.
Surely we accomplished a lot in building more sophisticated thermostats.
AI also helped us in the sciences but it may be the case that we did not come any closer towards creating <em>human intelligence</em>.
The overenthusiasm of the tech-industry is slowly crumbeling and a period of disillusionment is on the horizon.
Maybe this gives us the possibility to breathe and think about the technology we really wanna create and use.</p>

<h2 id="creativity">Creativity</h2>

<p>The question we discussed at the penal that is exciting and frightening at the same time is:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To what extent can artificial intelligence challenge human creativity?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So far, we have established a clear difference between <em>human</em> and <em>artificial intelligence</em>.
If creativity requires intelligence, does the question under this assumption matter?</p>

<p>Before tackling this question, we have to define or at least get an intuitive idea of what we mean by <em>creativity</em>.
This is, of course, a complex and maybe even impossible task.</p>

<p>First, we can attribute creativity to a subject, object or process.
A creative product or idea has to be <strong>novel</strong> and <strong>useful</strong> (which might be highly subjective).
The product might just be aesthetically pleasing (or even disgusting), which is in itself useful.
Novelty, as well as usefulness, can be either <em>psychological (P)</em>, i.e., it is novel/useful to the agent that produces it, or <em>historical (H)</em>, i.e., novel/useful to society.</p>

<p>Every human being is creative.
In other words, creativity is not reserved for a special elite; instead, it is a feature of human intelligence in general.
Creativity involves everyday capacities, e.g., perception, searching for a structure, reminding, and combining concepts.</p>

<p>Lastly, creativity involves motivation and emotion and is closely linked to historical, political, cultural, social and personal/subjective factors.</p>

<h2 id="artificial-creativity">Artificial Creativity</h2>

<p>In her article <em>Creativity and Artificial Intelligence</em> <a class="citation" href="#boden:1998">(Boden, 1998)</a> <em>M. A. Boden</em> lists three ways to create new ideas:</p>

<ol>
  <li>combination of familiar ideas</li>
  <li>exploration of the conceptual space</li>
  <li>transformation of previously impossible ideas</li>
</ol>

<p>Since creative products have to be novel and useful, artificial creative systems are typically structured into two phases:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>generation</strong> and</li>
  <li><strong>evaluation</strong>.</li>
</ol>

<p>Artificial intelligence can help us with the generation.
Algorithms can realize all three ways of idea creation, but at some point in the process, subjective factors have to come into play.
Machines and algorithms are not motivated by anything; they are not emotional.</p>

<p>Let us look at a famous example: the proof of <em>the four-color problem</em>.
The four-color problem asks if it is possible to color a map in such a way that there are no two adjacent parts with the same color, using only four colors.
It was proven in 1976 by <em>Kenneth Appel</em> and <em>Wolfgang Haken</em> with the help of a computer.
Four colors are enough!
An algorithm helped check different possibilities.
Clearly, the machine is part of the creative process of proving a mathematical statement, but at the same time, it is instructed by the programmers who injected their subjective motivation and cultural background.
They decided to take up the task of proving the statement.
They decided it was worth their time and developed a strategy that a machine could execute.</p>

<p>No artificial intelligence decided to prove <em>the four-color problem</em>, but humans did.
Proving a mathematical statement does not start with the proof itself.
This point is important!
Scientists choose what they want to prove and what they think is essential.
This choice can not be reduced to an <em>objective, rational</em>; it is a <em>subjective evaluation of values and symbols of meaning</em>.
But to this day, machines can not infuse symbols with meaning.
They work on a purely syntactical level.</p>

<p>This is no argument against <em>simulated creativity</em>.
Artificial intelligence is perfectly suitable to find, generate, combine or create what we humans value and attach meaning to.
Therefore, AI can bring forth what we perceive to be creative.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In principle, artificial intelligence can create something novel that is meaningful to us.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For example, in August 2015, researchers from Tübingen created a convolutional neural network that uses neural representations to separate and recombine the content and style of arbitrary images.
The network can turn images into stylistic imitations of works of art by artists such as a <em>Picasso</em> or <em>Van Gogh</em> in about an hour.
In October 2018, the <a href="https://www.christies.com/features/A-collaboration-between-two-artists-one-human-one-a-machine-9332-1.aspx">Portrait of Edmond de Belamy</a>, an algorithm-generated print, was sold for $432 500.
In both cases, the AI (1) combined familiar ideas, (2) explored a conceptual space, and (3) transformed previously impossible ideas.</p>

<h2 id="disruptions-and-control">Disruptions and Control</h2>

<p>Humans have created and enjoyed all art forms for viewing, aesthetic, and even therapeutic purposes.
We should not forget that technology has impacted how art is created and enjoyed for the last 100 years.
The invention of <em>portable paint tubes</em>, for example, enabled artists to paint outdoors and sparked a contingent of stunning landscape and horizon paintings.
Today cameras and software like <em>Photoshop</em> have redefined how art is created and enjoyed.
Even if we disagree on what art is, it is safe to say that these technological advances have not changed our antiquated meaning of it.</p>

<p>Regardless of the technology, there was always some human intervention required to create art.
Since machines can not make sense of our social, cultural, transcendental, and physical world, I highly doubt that this will change in the near future.
As long as we fail in creating <em>human intelligence</em>, there is no reason to believe that <em>artificial intelligence</em> can replace the human artist.
But why do we even want to create <em>human intelligence</em>?
Why shall we copy ourselves?</p>

<p>Technologies got introduced long before the digital era.
However, what changed is <em>the speed of disruption</em>.
At the rate at which technology is being accepted in every industry, it is no longer difficult to imagine a future of fewer artists.
The increased usage of all kinds of AI in all kinds of art suggests that it is here to stay.
From AI-written books, such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1_the_Road">The Road</a>, to blooming tulip videos, creators have found value in utilizing artificial intelligence.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We all hope for a world where our technologies help us and not replace us.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Our current technologically and competitively driven economic system neglects any profound confrontation with technology.
Competition leads to <em>the fear of missing out</em>; of losing some advantage over others.
We are so used to technology, comforted by it, and convinced that it has become our new religion – at least for some of us.
We lost the distinction between <em>technological progress</em> and <em>evolution</em>.
Now, technology <strong>is</strong> evolution.
We no longer think about it. 
Instead, if it is properly marketed and channeled into our desires, we buy and use it.</p>

<p>Every broadly accepted new technology leads to disruption.
The increasing speed of disruption makes it more and more difficult to attach meaning to the new.
Solid structures get replaced by a liquid stream of information.
We can no longer get too invested in something because it might be replaced the next day.
Artists might be in trouble if this superficiality becomes a reality in the art world.</p>

<p>In the article <em><a href="https://medium.com/@francois.chollet/what-worries-me-about-ai-ed9df072b704">What worries me about AI</a></em>, <em>Francois Chollet</em> states his personal opinion about the real destructive potential of AI; he hits the mark.
First, he convincingly argues that we are painfully bad at predicting future threats but we can be easily driven towards illusive fears.
For example, who could forecast that the transportation and manufacturing technologies we were developing would enable a new form of industrial warfare that would wipe out tens of millions in two World Wars?
According to Chollet, the danger is not the singularity of AI; it is not about automation and job replacement; aligned with <em><a href="https://www.ynharari.com/de/">Yuval Noah Harari</a></em>, he states it is about hacking human societies, and I have to agree.
Brexit and other political disruptions already show a trend.
When consumption and creation mainly happen in the digital world, we become vulnerable to that which rules it – AI algorithms.
And these AI algorithms serve the interest of big corporations and governments, i.e., aggregations of power.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We’re looking at a company that builds fine-grained psychological profiles of almost two billion humans, that serves as a primary news source for many of them, that runs large-scale behavior manipulation experiments, and that aims at developing the best AI technology the world has ever seen. Personally, it scares me. – <em>Francois Chollet</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The history of psychological tricks applied by marketing and advertisers was born with the introduction of surplus production.
It started with <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Bernays">Edward Louis Bernays</a></em>, a nephew of <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigmund_Freud">Sigmund Freud</a></em> and horrific misanthrope with grand ambitions.
His story is worth studying.
Today, <em>accessibility</em> and <em>AI</em> guarantees constant exposure to this resonating and highly individualized noise.
<em>Reinforcement learning</em> can easily be applied to whole human societies.
Algorithms can decide what you see; they show you things you identify with to trick you into a particular belief.
They can channel your unwanted opinions to a specific group of people, who will reject and oppose you.
Constant rejection can then lead to alienation.
This combination of <em>identification</em> and <em>alienation</em> can gently force you into <em>adaptations</em>.
The system can potentially punish what it does not want to see; it can <em>train</em> you into the “correct” mindset.</p>

<p>I think we have to educate ourselves not only about AI but how we can be manipulated by it.
In the past, we learned about the influence of pollution on the quality of life.
We have regulations for fine particles, chemicals, and CO2 emissions.
Now it is time to learn about the pollution of our mind.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We have to learn about the pollution of our mind.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We need transparency and control for the public and the customer.
I want to be in charge of the objective function of <em>YouTube’s</em> algorithms feeding me with suggestions.
I want to decide on what bases I will be manipulated.
Paradoxically enough, AI can help us with these tasks.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The issue is not AI itself. The issue is control. – <em>Francois Chollet</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Of course, this would destroy most business models; thus, corporations will not implement these changes voluntarily.
Governments are another beast.
Right now, it is unimaginable that China will change its way of using AI and Western governments are not innocent either.</p>

<p>AI will be, most likely, part of our future life – our window to the world made of digital information.
As I stated in my <a href="/Pages/2021/06/08/Informatics-a-love-letter.html">love letter</a>, informatics and AI can be empowering disciplines.
AI can emancipate us.
But it can also lead to a total loss of self-determination and agency.
I believe we still have enough leftover to steer the wheel in the right direction.</p>

<p>In the progress of a possible democratization of AI, art could play a major role.
Art, as an aesthetic counterpart to the kind of destructive advertisement polluting our thoughts, can reveal its manipulative power.
Future artists might have to revolt against <em>the speed of disruption</em>.
Artwork may be the product of technology, but <strong>also</strong> offers a window into it.
Maybe in art lies the possibility, on the one hand, to disengage, but also to profoundly engage with technology;
to reveal who is in charge for what reason;
To ask: What is it good for?
How does it change our social, economic, political, and transcendental systems?
Can everyday people control it, and if so, how can we get there?</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<ol class="bibliography"><li><span id="mccarthy:1998">McCarthy, J. (1998). <i>What is artificial intelligence?</i></span></li>
<li><span id="turing:1950">Turing, A. M. (1950). Computing Machinery and Intelligence. <i>Mind</i>, <i>59</i>(236), 433–460. http://www.jstor.org/stable/2251299</span></li>
<li><span id="russel:2010">Russell, S., &amp; Norvig, P. (2010). <i>Artificial Intelligence: A Modern Approach</i> (3rd ed.). Prentice Hall.</span></li>
<li><span id="lee:2010">Lee, D. (2021). <i>Birth of Intelligence: From RNA to Artificial Intelligence.</i> New York: Oxford University Press.</span></li>
<li><span id="liu:2017">Liu, S., &amp; Spelke, E. S. (2017). Six-month-old infants expect agents to minimize the cost of their actions. <i>Cognition</i>, <i>160</i>, 35–42. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cognition.2016.12.007</span></li>
<li><span id="olson:2008">Olson, K. R., &amp; Spelke, E. S. (2008). Foundations of cooperation in young children. <i>Cognition</i>, <i>108</i>(1), 222–231. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cognition.2007.12.003</span></li>
<li><span id="boden:1998">Boden, M. A. (1998). Creativity and artificial intelligence. <i>Artificial Intelligence</i>, <i>103</i>(1), 347–356. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0004-3702(98)00055-1</span></li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Benedikt Zönnchen</name><email>benedikt.zoennchen@web.de</email></author><category term="Opinion" /><category term="AI" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Panel Discussion]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interactive Computational Thinking</title><link href="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/10/27/computational-thinking-with-python.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interactive Computational Thinking" /><published>2021-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/10/27/computational-thinking-with-python</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/10/27/computational-thinking-with-python.html"><![CDATA[<p>Currently, I am working as a lecturer at the <a href="https://www.cs.hm.edu/en/home/index.en.html">Munich University of Applied Sciences (MUAS)</a> for the course <strong>Computational Thinking</strong>.
We decided to use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Python</code> as our primary programming language.
To provide students with a textbook that covers our content and is stylistically sound, we decided to test out the Jupyter ecosystem, i.e., the <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/intro.html">Jupyter book</a> technology.</p>

<p>Furthermore, we decided to publish the unfinished book publicly.
It is a work in progress, and I will work on it during the semesters.
The book is written in German.
We may translate it into English in the future.</p>

<ul>
  <li>The book is available here: <a href="https://bzoennchen.github.io/ct-book/intro.html">Computational Thinking</a></li>
  <li>The source code of the book is available here: <a href="https://github.com/BZoennchen/ct-book">Source of the book</a></li>
</ul>

<p>We will see how our students will receive the book.
In my opinion, the <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/intro.html">Jupyter book</a> technology covers many features to write an excellent online book.
I will use the technology for other future projects.</p>

<p>If you like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LaTeX</code> as I do, <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/intro.html">Jupyter book</a> might also be something worth your time.
It offers similar features, and the working flow is very similar.
One can reference external sources (you can even include a BibTex file), internal sections, figures, equations, and definitions.
On top of that, the reader can execute the code directly within the book (for Python) and on Binder or another Service providing Jupyter Notebooks if the correct kernel is available.
I only tried this with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Python</code>, but this should also work for other languages such as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Java</code>.</p>

<p>It is less flexible than <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LaTeX</code> because one is bound to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">HTML</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CSS</code>, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">JavaScript</code>.
For example, positioning tables and figures differently than intended is pretty tricky – I have given up on it.
The intelligence of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LaTeX</code> is also missing, e.g., no automatic hyphenation.
Aside from executing code directly within the document, another advantage is the referencing.
As a reader, It is much easier to navigate a well-referenced web page than navigate a large PDF file.</p>

<p>Overall, I quite like it!</p>]]></content><author><name>Benedikt Zönnchen</name><email>benedikt.zoennchen@web.de</email></author><category term="Education" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Currently, I am working as a lecturer at the Munich University of Applied Sciences (MUAS) for the course Computational Thinking. We decided to use Python as our primary programming language. To provide students with a textbook that covers our content and is stylistically sound, we decided to test out the Jupyter ecosystem, i.e., the Jupyter book technology.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Informatics - A Love Letter</title><link href="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/06/08/Informatics-a-love-letter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Informatics - A Love Letter" /><published>2021-06-08T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/06/08/Informatics-a-love-letter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/06/08/Informatics-a-love-letter.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>“The objection that computing is not a science because it studies man-made objects (technologies) is a red herring. Computer science studies information processes both artificial and natural.” – Peter J. Denning <a class="citation" href="#denning:2005">(Denning, 2005)</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>For me personally, informatics is an empowering discipline - it is part of the emancipation of men. 
Its engineering quality can directly enable our fragile and limited body and mind. 
But its magic goes beyond practical use. Similar to mathematics, we discover its beauty in an abstract world. 
This Platonian world consists of fantastic, imaginative objects we can recognize, build and play with. 
In it, the problems of men are absent. 
There is no morality, no judgment, no conflict, no othering but harmony to enjoy, complex structures to discover, riddles to unravel, and logic-based creativity to get lost in.</p>

<h2 id="informatics-is-an-art">Informatics is an Art</h2>

<p>In popular culture, coding is often portrayed as something conspicuously ‘nerdy’ and alienating.
A usually white ‘<em>creepy</em>’ man writes his code by typing seamlessly and rapidly into a black terminal.
He never stops, he never interacts with other beings, and he never leaves his desk.
Of course, everything works perfectly on the first try, and no one else seems to have any clue what’s going on.
Intellectually, the programmer stands above everyone else; he is a genius, a mad scientist, or an introverted weirdo - only so important to do the necessary work and enable the ‘real’ hero.
This toxic depiction of software developers (and introverted people) is wrong, dated, and was never accurate in the first place.</p>

<p>From the outside, coding looks like the most boring thing on Earth.
This assessment is, of course, utterly wrong!
Writing programs is a beautiful, creative and interactive process.
To somebody who does it, it is the most exciting thing in the world.
It is a game of chess but much more involving because you can make up your own rules and build your own world.
Elementary entities accumulate to something bigger, something interconnected.
The degree of freedom and creativity this process of creation offers can hardly be explained or understood if one never experienced it first-hand.</p>

<p>In no way does programming start in isolation at the computer, nor can we do it seamlessly.
It is neither a strictly analytical nor a purely experimental process.
Like writing an exciting story, it is a struggle, always!
If it isn’t, we or someone else has already solved the puzzle - the exciting part has been gone.
In that case, we do not create but translate.</p>

<p>One of the fascinating facts is that, in the end, everything comes down to simple symbol manipulations, which we call information processes.
Software developers scoop, transform, and use information.
They design data structures and algorithms like architects draw construction plans.
Additionally, they have the power to build, combine, reuse and extend those objects of structured information.
They command machines of blind obedience.
The degree of control translates to a form of power and self-determination absent in the physical world.
As Linus Torvalds rightfully noted:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“[Phyisics and computer science] are about how the world works at a rather fundamental level. The difference, of course, is that while in physics, you are supposed to figure out how the world is made up, in computer science, you create the world. Within the confines of the computer, you are the creator. You get ultimate control over everything that happens. If you are good enough, you can be God on a small scale.” – Linus Torvalds</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In contrast to most other kinds of engineers, software developers can use a highly flexible and versatile resource.
Information can be easily exchanged among peers, reshaped, conceptually described, and analyzed.
In fact, it manipulates itself since any program is nothing more than well-structured information.
Like many other materialized ideas, structured information arises from human thoughts; they result from a mental exercise.
But the transformation of thoughts into objects of structured information is immediate.
It is like writing a poem.
Therefore, it can be an entirely personal and connecting experience to read the code, i.e., thoughts, of someone else.
Over time, one learns to appreciate good code - its structure, aesthetic, modularity, level of abstraction, simplicity, consistency, and elegance.</p>

<p>By learning different programming languages, one learns different perspectives. I love <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Python</code>’s lists notation and that functions are first-class entities.
But I’m not too fond of the indent notation.
The success of a programming language is bound to its popularity. Do developers like it?
Is it joyful to write code? Learning different programming languages taught me something about our natural language: the language I use forms my thoughts.
If a statement can be efficiently and aesthetically pleasingly expressed in a certain way, programmers will choose that way.
And sometimes, they overuse it. Furthermore, programmers look at a problem and go through their catalog of elegant expressions to find the one that fits.
A programming language not only determines what we can express but also introduces a particular bias in how we will express it.
The same is true for our natural language. 
This seems not like a revolutionary insight, but we forget this fact in our daily life. 
A change in language might have a more significant impact on material changes than we think.
Furthermore, this also highlights a fundamental problem of the human condition: we need abstractions and standards to communicate with each other.
But by using abstractions, we distance ourselves from others.</p>

<p>If we look beyond the code, beyond ideas written down in text snippets, programs are written to be executed.
And those programs can serve almost any domain.
They control robots, harvest semantic information, control networks of devices, and simulate the natural world and other virtual worlds.
They establish communication channels, send messages with the speed of light across the Earth, compose and play music, and constantly search for structures in a rapidly increasing cloud of data points.</p>

<p>However, in the end, functionality is second to being exciting or pretty.
Even coding itself is secondary.
Figuring out how things work is the real deal.
Since everything is self-consistent and logical, you can go on and on and never stop exploring.
It is an endless stream, too immense for one lifetime.
And you are not even bound to some external logic; you can make up your own as long as it is consistent.
This consistency is a bright contrast to the corporate, social, and political world - it’s like going home to a place where everything is comprehensible, a place where you can find some truth within the bounds of its rules.</p>

<h2 id="informatics-is-a-science">Informatics is a Science</h2>

<p>As a software engineer, I want to build large architectures that process information.
I want to express myself through code.
In the world of physical objects, we have to study the properties of certain materials and the laws of physics to guarantee that our buildings do not collapse and rockets behave as expected.
But how can we specify and verify structured information?
How can we even define what we can compute?
What is computable?
Is sorting cards equally <em>hard</em> as solving a Sudoku?
Here we enter yet another world, a formal one!</p>

<p>Of course, those two worlds are never entirely separated.
Formal methods and objects, like the Turing Machine, the Lambda Calculus, logic, grammars, and automata are the mathematical backbones of informatics.
They are a particular kind of mathematically rigorous description of information manipulation (computation).
By analyzing those objects, we get to the very fundamental and interesting questions.
I was never hooked by the purpose of formal methods in software development (verification and specification).
Instead, I found them intrinsically fascinating!
It was just enough to discover these formal, therefore, clearly defined objects.
Again, it is tough to explain this attraction.</p>

<p>You start with a set of unambiguous definitions: an alphabet, a word over an alphabet, a tuple of a set of states, a transition function, etc.
And you begin to construct slightly more and more powerful objects while analyzing the properties of these objects.
You always try to keep their power controllable.
Their properties should stay computable - you enter the realm of constructivism.
You begin to recognize the equivalence of objects from entirely different fields, such as logic and automata theory.
And you form beautiful proofs about very abstract thus general statements of your formally constructed world.</p>

<p>At some point, you arrive at a formal model of any digital computer, that is, the <em>Turing Machine</em>.
Since you now have this gift, this formal model, you can analyze it in a highly abstract way.
You can define what a computer at least requires to be <em>Turing-complete</em>, i.e., to be a computer.
You can define what <em>computable</em> means, and you can even measure how many steps it takes to solve a class of problems.
You start analyzing the <em>complexity</em> of problems, such as sorting cards or solving a Sudoku.</p>

<p>For example, sorting cards (on a <em>Turing-complete</em> model) requires \(\mathcal{O}(n\log(n))\) steps, where \(n\) is the number of cards.
And we know that we can not do better than that.
Consequently, in the worst case, sorting cards requires always at least \(c \cdot n\log(n)\) steps where \(c\) is some constant independent of \(n\).
Isn’t that captivating that we know this!</p>

<p>Then there is the still <strong>unanswered</strong> question if solving a Sudoku is as <em>hard</em> as checking a solution of it?
We call this</p>

\[\mathcal{NP} \stackrel{?}{=} \mathcal{P}\]

<p><em>problem</em>. Of course, we ask again in the context of <em>Turing Machines</em>.
Therefore, one might argue that this is not a scientific question because we ask for some property of some human-made machine.
I strongly disagree!
This machine is a mathematical object, and mathematics is the language of nature.
To this day, <em>Turing Machines</em> are THE model for computation (Lambda Calculus is equivalent);
a Turing Machine can simulate even quantum computers.
If nature does compute, we might even study its basic principles!
Doesn’t it feel <em>harder</em> to solve a Sudoku than to check its solution?
Isn’t there a fundamental difference?
Or isn’t finding a proof much harder than understanding it.</p>

<p>Finding a solution involves what we call creativity and intuition.
But checking it is a rather automatable process.
So if we reframe the question, we may ask about the complexity of creativity!
Since hundreds of publications falsely claimed to have solved the question, it seems to require a lot of creativity to correctly grasp the complexity of creativity.</p>

<p>What a fascinating scientific question to tackle!
We are in the realm of not natural science but similar to mathematics, a formal science.</p>

<p>Eventually, you encounter another significant problem: the <em>Halting problem</em>.
It states that there will never be a program (definable as a Turing Machine) that can test for an arbitrary program that it halts.
Understanding the theorem and its proof in-depth feels groundbreaking and infinitely satisfying.
The proof is simple and beautiful if you understand how computers, i.e., <em>Turing Machines</em>, work.
You can find a sketch of it in the appendix of this article.</p>

<h2 id="the-evolution-of-informatics">The Evolution of Informatics</h2>

<h3 id="roots-of-informatics">Roots of Informatics</h3>

<p>It is kind of funny that historically, informatics first struggled for recognition on a global scale.
In academia, this struggle has been gone.
However, in the general public’s eye, the objective and research subject of the discipline is blurred, which still leads to confusion:
yes, I am a computer scientist, but I won’t fix your computer or software bugs!</p>

<p>If we look into the history books, computer scientists had to fight to establish their field.
The discipline emerged from certain branches such as electrical engineering, physics, and mathematics.
In the 1960s, computer science comes into its own as a discipline. Georg Forsythe, a numerical analyst, coined the term.
The first computer science department was formed at Purdue University in 1962.
The first person to receive a PhD from a computer science department was Richard Wexelblat, at the University of Pennsylvania, in December 1965.</p>

<p>In Germany, informatics goes back to the Institute for Practical Mathematics (IPM) at the Technische Hochschule Darmstadt, founded around 1928.
But it required time to establish the first informatics course in the Faculty of Electrical Engineering in Darmstadt.
The first doctoral thesis was written in 1975, ten years later compared to the US.
In my hometown, the first informatics course at the Technical University of Munich was offered in 1967 at the Department of Mathematics.
In 1992, the Department of Informatics split up from the Department of Mathematics.</p>

<p>Informatics can still be regarded as relatively young compared to other well-established disciplines such as physics, chemistry, or psychology. Nonetheless, new fields split up from informatics, and they are all interlinked with one another. We have, for example,</p>

<ul>
  <li>scientific computing,</li>
  <li>computational science,</li>
  <li>information theory,</li>
  <li>and linguistics,</li>
</ul>

<p>and the list goes on.
The problem of artificial intelligence (AI) brings informatics more and more in touch with the humanities such as</p>

<ul>
  <li>philosophy,</li>
  <li>psychology,</li>
  <li>and neurosciences.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-disappearance-of-classical-informatics">The Disappearance of ‘Classical’ Informatics?</h3>

<p>Within the field of informatics, there are a lot of branches one can pursue, for example:</p>

<ul>
  <li>formal methods and complexity theory</li>
  <li>programming languages and compilers</li>
  <li>design and analysis of algorithms and data structures</li>
  <li>parallel and distributed computation</li>
  <li>high-performance computation</li>
  <li>networks and communication</li>
  <li>intelligent systems</li>
  <li>operating systems</li>
  <li>cybersecurity</li>
  <li>databases</li>
  <li>data science</li>
  <li>computer graphics</li>
  <li>image processing</li>
  <li>modeling and simulation</li>
  <li>artificial intelligence</li>
  <li>software engineering</li>
  <li>architecture and organization</li>
</ul>

<p>This sprawling list of specialties indicates no longer such thing as a classical computer scientist, right? 
Nobody can be an expert in all areas - it is just impossible! Over the years, some branches lost, and others gained attraction, but most are active.
For example, we lost interest in operating systems but put more effort into investigating high-performance computation and data science.
Theoretical informatics cooled down, but there are still many critical questions unanswered.</p>

<p>Despite this abundant variety, being a computer scientist is more than being an expert in one specific field.
It is more than knowing how to build large software systems, manage networks, process data and establish a secure infrastructure.
<strong>It is a way of thinking!</strong> And no, we do not think like computers but embrace the curiosity naturally given to us human beings.
We renew the playing child within us and let it go wild to solve riddles for no particular reason. 
And I think that is one of the most human things to do.</p>

<h3 id="a-new-perspective-on-information">A New Perspective on Information</h3>

<p>In this little supplementary section, I want to talk about the resource we are working with: information.</p>

<p>As you may notice, I call <strong>computer science</strong> by the European term <strong>informatics</strong>.
But not only because I am from Europe but also because the term leans more towards <strong>information</strong> instead of <strong>computation</strong>.
Information manipulation is computation, but it emphasizes a more abstract broader definition of computation.</p>

<p>Information, as we understand it is the elimination of uncertainties but on a purely <strong>syntactical</strong> level.
This notion dated back to 1948 and was defined by Claude E. Shannon in <em>A Mathematical Theory of Communication</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Frequently, the messages have meaning; that is, they refer to or are correlated according to some system with certain physical or conceptual entities.
These semantic aspects of communication are irrelevant to the engineering problem.
The significant aspect is that the actual message is one selected from a set of possible messages.
The system has to be designed to operate for each possible selection, not just the one which will actually be chosen since this is unknown at the time of design.” – Claude E. Shannon <a class="citation" href="#shannon:1948">(Shannon, 1948)</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the humanities, researchers have a completely different understanding of information.
They discuss cognition, representations, referencing, and interpretation in the context of information.
What does a symbol mean, and what effect or interpretation does it has?
How does data transform into information, and how do we harvest knowledge and wisdom?</p>

<p>For the purpose of information transmitted via a technical channel, a purely syntactical perspective is appropriate.
But it seems inappropriate if we discuss today’s information-driven society.</p>

<p>Nowadays, we can rapidly collect unimaginable amounts of information.
It can be processed automatically and checked for higher-level patterns that would not be discernible without technology.
We constantly transform information into a machine-readable format, which makes it, in turn, quantifiable.
But is there information that is not machine-readable, and do we dismiss it?</p>

<p>Furthermore, the interconnected world of information processes of today never forgets anything.
Incessantly, it sucks up data and floods our private and public spaces with it.
It is like a magical beast that can create amazing miracles but can also cause devastating destructions - sometimes it appears as a lovely creature, and sometimes it embodies a frightening monster.
We have to deal with it!
It is our creation - an artificial intelligence that already evaluates, categorizes, interprets, and generates information on its own.
It has to include the semantics of information. 
Otherwise, it would be difficult to call it <em>artificial intelligence</em>.</p>

<p>Since we left the task of pure information transformation a long time ago, we need the perspective of the humanities - we have to think beyond pure syntax.
In fact, we have to reconsider the term <em>information</em>, at least in our discipline.
For example, Ulrich states:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Where data are the raw facts of the world, information is then data ‘with meaning’.
When ‘data’ acquires context-dependent meaning and relevance, it becomes information. 
Furthermore, we obviously expect information to represent valid knowledge on which users can rely for rational action. – W. Ulrich <a class="citation" href="#ulrich:2001">(Ulrich, 2001)</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>But even this definition seems problematic.
Is there even something like simple brute facts of the world?
All data seem to be already gathered and processed.
Therefore, information can not simply be the injection of meaning into data because data already has meaning.
It is more like the individual degree of significance differs.
What might be meaningful to me might be utterly meaningless to you.</p>

<p>Of course, we can not answer this question of an adequate definition here.
But to disregard it entirely and leave the design of interconnected information processes solely to the technicians would be a mistake.
Discovering, studying, using, influencing, and extending our interconnected world of information processing, is exciting as well as necessary.
It is part of our duties, but we should no longer encounter this beast alone.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="appendix">Appendix</h2>

<h3 id="the-halting-problem">The Halting Problem</h3>

<p>Let me try to give you the intuition of the <em>Halting problem</em>.
For simplicity reasons, I will not explicitly distinguish between a <em>Turing Machine</em> \(\mathcal{T}\) and its description (often noted by \(\alpha_\mathcal{T}\)).
So when a <em>Turing Machine</em> gets as input another <em>Turing Machine</em>, I mean its description (source code).</p>

<h4 id="proof">Proof</h4>

<p>Let us assume there is a <em>Turing Machine</em> \(\mathcal{H}\) that takes an arbitrary <em>Turing Machine</em> \(\mathcal{T}\) as input.
\(\mathcal{H}(\mathcal{T})\) outputs 1 if \(\mathcal{T}(\mathcal{T})\) halts, otherwise it outputs 0.
So if such a program exists, \(\mathcal{H}\) is the program that solves the <em>Halting problem</em>, and \(\mathcal{T}\) is an arbitrary program.
We can pick \(\mathcal{T}\) as its own input because the input can be arbitrary (but finite).
So we ‘feed’ the program \(\mathcal{T}\) with itself, that is, its own description/source code \(\mathcal{T}\).</p>

<p>So we have</p>

\[\begin{equation} \tag{1}\label{eq:halt:1}
\mathcal{H}(\mathcal{T}) = 
\begin{cases}
1, &amp; \text{if } \mathcal{T}(\mathcal{T}) \text{ halts} \\
0, &amp; \text{otherwise.}
\end{cases}
\end{equation}\]

<p>We construct a new <em>Turing Machine</em> \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}\).
\(\hat{\mathcal{H}}\) is a slight modification of \(\mathcal{H}\).
It does almost the opposite.
\(\hat{\mathcal{H}}\) halts and outputs 1 if and only if \(\mathcal{H}\) outputs 0.
Furthermore, \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}\) does not halt if \(\mathcal{H}\) outputs 1.</p>

\[\begin{equation} \tag{2}\label{eq:halt:2}
\hat{\mathcal{H}}(\mathcal{T}) = 
\begin{cases}
1, &amp; \text{if } \mathcal{H}(\mathcal{T}) = 0 \\
\text{undefined, i.e., loops endlessly} &amp; \text{if } \mathcal{H}(\mathcal{T}) = 1
\end{cases}
\end{equation}\]

<p><br /></p>
<div><img style="display:block;margin:auto;;height:200px;" src="/Pages/assets/images/halting-problem.png" alt="Halting Proglem" /></div>
<p><br />
Now we execute \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}\) by feeding it to itself, that is, \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}(\hat{\mathcal{H}})\) and analyse the result:</p>

<p><strong>It outputs 1:</strong>
Let us assume \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}(\hat{\mathcal{H}}) = 1\).
Following Eq. \eqref{eq:halt:2} gives us \(\mathcal{H}(\hat{\mathcal{H}}) = 0\).
But by following Eq. \eqref{eq:halt:1} this implies that \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}(\hat{\mathcal{H}})\) does not halt.
After all, \(\mathcal{H}\) outputs 0.
Thus, it recognizes that the analyzed program \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}\) does not halt.
But if \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}(\hat{\mathcal{H}})\) does not halt, it follows by Eq. \eqref{eq:halt:2} that \(\mathcal{H}(\hat{\mathcal{H}}) = 1\) which leads to a contradiction.</p>

<p><strong>It outputs 0:</strong>
Let us assume \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}(\hat{\mathcal{H}}) = \text{undefined}\).
\(\mathcal{H}(\hat{\mathcal{H}}) = 1\) follows from Eq. \eqref{eq:halt:2} which implies that \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}(\hat{\mathcal{H}})\) does halts, compare Eq. \eqref{eq:halt:1}.
But if \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}(\hat{\mathcal{H}})\) halts then by following Eq. \eqref{eq:halt:2}, \(\mathcal{H}(\hat{\mathcal{H}}) = 0\) which leads to a contradiction.</p>

<p>In any case \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}(\hat{\mathcal{H}})\) leads to a paradox!
However, the construction of \(\hat{\mathcal{H}}\) is correct if  \(\mathcal{H}\) exists.
Therefore, it follows that our assumption is wrong and \(\mathcal{H}\) can not exists!</p>

<h4 id="meaning">Meaning</h4>

<p>The <em>Halting problem</em> is strongly connected to the question of <strong>decidability</strong>.
It asks if, for some problem or statement, an algorithm or a proof solves the problem in a finite number of steps or proves the statement.
As we saw, the <em>Halting problem</em> is <strong>undecidable</strong>!
Any <em>Turing-complete</em> machine or system is <strong>undecidable</strong>, and there are many such systems!
For example:</p>

<ul>
  <li>complex quantum systems,</li>
  <li>the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_Game_of_Life">Game of Life</a>,</li>
  <li>airline ticketing systems</li>
  <li>the card game Magic,</li>
  <li>and, of course, almost any programming language is <em>Turing-complete</em>.</li>
</ul>

<p>There are three essential properties for a desirable mathematical system, and we may think they are fulfilled naturally.
But as it turns out, this is not the case.
We would like to have a system that is</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>complete</strong>: any statement of the system can be proven or disproven</li>
  <li><strong>consistent</strong>: a statement can not be proven and disproven at the same time</li>
  <li>and <strong>decidable</strong>: an algorithm (proof) requires a finite number of steps to prove or disprove any statement</li>
</ol>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurt_G%C3%B6del">Kurt Gödel</a> showed that any decently functional mathematical system is either <strong>incomplete</strong> or <strong>inconsistent</strong>.
Later, he also showed that even if such a system is <strong>consistent</strong>, this can not be proven within the system.
After <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Turing">Alan Turing</a> found a computation model, the <em>Turing Machine</em>, he showed that</p>

<ol>
  <li>many problems / systems are <em>Turing-complete</em></li>
  <li>all those systems are <strong>undecidable</strong>.</li>
</ol>

<p>This revelation crushed the mathematical landscape and ended the dream of David Hilbert and others to establish a solid mathematical foundation.
Sadly, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurt_G%C3%B6del">Kurt Gödel</a>, as well as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Turing">Alan Turing</a>, one of the most brilliant minds, died tragically.</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<ol class="bibliography"><li><span id="denning:2005">Denning, P. J. (2005). Is Computer Science Science? <i>Commun. ACM</i>, <i>48</i>(4), 27–31. https://doi.org/10.1145/1053291.1053309</span></li>
<li><span id="shannon:1948">Shannon, C. E. (1948). A Mathematical Theory of Communication. <i>Bell Syst. Tech. J.</i>, <i>27</i>(3), 379–423.</span></li>
<li><span id="ulrich:2001">Ulrich, W. (2001). <i>A Philosophical Staircase for Information Systems Definition</i>.</span></li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Benedikt Zönnchen</name><email>benedikt.zoennchen@web.de</email></author><category term="Opinion" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“The objection that computing is not a science because it studies man-made objects (technologies) is a red herring. Computer science studies information processes both artificial and natural.” – Peter J. Denning (Denning, 2005)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PhD Defense</title><link href="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/06/05/phd-defense.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PhD Defense" /><published>2021-06-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/06/05/phd-defense</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/06/05/phd-defense.html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I just wanna note that I finally finished my academic journey on the 21st of Mai by successfully defending my PhD thesis.
The thesis will be published very soon and I post it here on this website.</p>

<p>The following text is from the preface of the thesis and describes my personal struggles during and my perspective on the journey.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The struggle itself towards the heights is enough to fill a man’s heart. One must imagine Sisyphus happy.” – Albert Camus</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="my-personal-journey">My Personal Journey</h2>

<p>I can pinpoint the exact moment when I decided to start my academic journey. At that time, my life was harshly disrupted by physical illness and the death of my father. Consequently, my family struggled on many levels. Despite, and probably because of the unfortunate circumstances and with my family’s blessing, I quit my job and rejoined school to get my (technical) A level. I wanted to comprehend the world more than ever and escape the meaningless play of presenting. At that difficult time, there was a financial intensive to graduate as fast as possible. Therefore, I did not join the university but the computer science program at the Munich University of Applied Sciences.</p>

<p>During my undergraduate study, my former naive belief was crushed. I realized that I would never find any definitive objective truth about the physical world. It was a rather pessimistic but also liberating philosophical revelation that there is no definitive rule to follow and no absolute meaning to fulfill. My search was no longer aimed to find an objective meaning but a personal cause to follow. I still admired studying but for other more aesthetic reasons. I loved the clarity and usefulness of formal systems, the beauty of proofs, the elegance of algorithms, and the stu- dent’s lifestyle. I observed a transforming world where computer science spread out into many branches of science, economics, and society. It was a time of playful experimentation and the deconstruction of personal barriers.</p>

<p>After I got my bachelor’s degree, I finally joined a master program at the Technical University of Munich. This continuation was enabled by the individual and financial support I received from Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes &amp; the Max Weber-Programm. I followed my aesthetic taste and visited rather unpopular formal lectures. At that time, I realized that the source of my personal cause to move on has to be bound to someone else. Beauty and aesthetic theories were a pleasant enjoyment, but they could no longer be the primary reason to live for.</p>

<p>Surprisingly my academic journey should not stop there, since Prof. Dr. Köster invited me into her research group. There are multiple reasons why I happily accepted her invitation. The desire to understand the world was reduced to the desire to understand at least one little part of it. Furthermore, I believed that simulations would influence science, economics, and society for decades to come. And if I could make the world a little bit safer, it might be the cause I was looking for.
During my PhD, the wish to be useful and to help others was always a source of inner conflict and self-doubt. I started the whole journey to escape a world that I perceived to be shallow, empty, and driven by profit. From time to time, the scientific research project felt like this meaningless business world that came back to haunt me. Luckily I was in a superb position. Everyone tried to reduce this aspect of the scientific environment to a minimum, for which I am very grateful.</p>

<p>I think every PhD candidate has to deal with uncertainties and self-doubt – the uncertainty within science and the uncertainty of the journey’s path. There is no guaranteed progress or graduation and one is constantly confronted with his or her own limitations. These factors and the ever-present questioning voice in my head acted as a catalyst for an unavoidable existential crisis. I looked into many philosophical ideas and rearranged, and possibly reinforced, my world view and many important values – the chapter’s introductory quotes tell the tale. In my opinion, this process was only possible, because during my academic journey I received the tools to engage with difficult ideas. On the one hand, this crisis was unpleasant but on the other hand it enriched my life – a trade-off I am certainly willing to repeat. In the end, I had supportive companions that helped me to deal with all these issues.
It was not easy, and I guess it rarely ever is, but the struggle is part of the charm – as Camus said,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“we must imagine Sisyphus happy.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For me, to study is to train thoughtful thinking, perception, awareness, and tolerance. It sharpens the mind and opens up a little less ignorant new world. The ability to enjoy thinking and to share this enjoyment with other thoughtful people provides freedom and independence. It might be the greatest gift I received during my journey. Because of it and the people I met, it is a success story, and I am deeply thankful that I could have experienced it.</p>]]></content><author><name>Benedikt Zönnchen</name><email>benedikt.zoennchen@web.de</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today, I just wanna note that I finally finished my academic journey on the 21st of Mai by successfully defending my PhD thesis. The thesis will be published very soon and I post it here on this website.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sound Design with SuperCollider</title><link href="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/03/27/super-collider-in-15-minutes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sound Design with SuperCollider" /><published>2021-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/03/27/super-collider-in-15-minutes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/03/27/super-collider-in-15-minutes.html"><![CDATA[<p>In the past, I did a 15-minute introduction for <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SuperCollider (SC)</a> for students at my University.
Likewise to Sonic Pi’s introduction, I will repeat everything I talked about and give some additional insights.</p>

<p><a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SC</a> can be used in many very different ways, such as algorithmic composition, sound design, research, and more.
In the following, I concentrate on sound design.</p>

<p>Note that there is a strong connection between <a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">Sonic Pi (SP)</a> and <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SC</a> since <a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">SP</a> uses <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SC</a> to generate sound, that is, <a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">SP</a> is used to implement a rhythm, but the actual sound comes from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code>s defined by <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SC</a> or samples.
Therefore, <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SC</a> and <a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">SP</a> can go hand in hand.
I also want to stress that one can implement rhythm and play samples using <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SC</a>, but a lot more code is required because <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SC</a> is much more low-level, i.e., more control but less rapid development.</p>

<h2 id="supercollider">SuperCollider</h2>

<p>I was motivated by my interest in education and first discovered <a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">Sonic Pi (SP)</a>.
In my opinion, it is a very powerful tool for educational purposes and live programming.
One can rapidly implement a beat or a rhythm and learn the basic concept of structured programming and threads.
Additional effects can be added to the pre-defined <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">synths</code>, and we can play around with different arguments but changing the sound by those techniques is still limited.
Overall, simplicity is achieved by a lack of control over the sound that is created.
This is not a critic.
<a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">Sonic Pi (SP)</a> is a fantastic project.</p>

<p>However, I wanted more power over what was happening, and since <a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">Sonic Pi (SP)</a> was built on top of <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SuperCollider (SC)</a>, I looked into it.
I most probably would not have got a grasp of it if I had not discovered the excellent tutorials of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/elifieldsteel">Eli Fieldsteel</a>, an Assistant Professor of Composition-Theory and Director of the Experimental Music Studios at The University of Illinois.
<a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SuperCollider (SC)</a> is a package of three components:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>scsynth</strong>: a real-time audio server, i.e., the part that plays the sound</li>
  <li><strong>sclang</strong>: an interpreted programming language focused on sound. The user can control <strong>scsynth</strong> by sending messages (Open Sound Control) to the audio server.</li>
  <li><strong>scide</strong>: an IDE for <strong>sclang</strong> with an integrated help system, analyzing tools, and a good documentation.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SuperCollider</a> is written in C++ and was developed by James McCartney and was originally released in 1996. In 2002, he generously released it as free software under the GNU General Public License. It is now maintained and developed by an active community.</p>

<p><a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">Sonic Pi (SP)</a> and other tools for algorithmic composition only use the audio server <strong>scsynth</strong> and replace the other parts with their own programming language and development environment.
Since <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SuperCollider</a> is around for some time, it is a very rich environment and language.
However, one can also observe some inconveniences and feel its age.
Nevertheless, it follows interesting concepts that were new to me, and whenever we see new coding paradigms and concepts, we learn something.</p>

<h2 id="programming-sound">Programming Sound</h2>

<p>First, let’s observe how the IDE interacts with the interpreter. 
To evaluate a line of code, we press <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">shift + return</code>, and to evaluate a code block, we press <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cmd + return</code> on the Mac and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">crtl + return</code> on Windows and Linux.</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="mf">10</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mf">3</span><span class="p">;</span>                     <span class="c1">// returns 13</span>
<span class="mf">4</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mf">5</span><span class="p">;</span>                      <span class="c1">// returns 9</span>
<span class="nc">Array</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">series</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">1</span><span class="p">);</span>     <span class="c1">// returns [0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9]</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><strong>Warning:</strong> One hotkey is very, very important, that is, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cmd + .</code>.
It stops all sound. 
<a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SC</a> will not protect you from creating a painful or very loud sound.
Where <a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">Sonic Pi (SP)</a> is rather safe, even a small typo can lead to a horrible and even damaging experience in <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SC</a>.
Therefore, I recommend using headphones, and before you listen to a new sound, put them off your head and make sure the sound will not blow you away!</p>

<h3 id="booting-the-server">Booting the Server</h3>

<p>I have written a simple extension <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Utils</code> which boots the server and initializes the windows, i.e., analyzing tools I often require.
The code can be found in <a href="https://github.com/BZoennchen/SuperCollider/blob/main/sc/extensions/classes/utils.sc">Utils</a>.</p>

<p>I call a class function to initialize everything I want:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">Utils</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">initTools</span><span class="p">();</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Note that as long as we do not have to communicate with the audio server, i.e., play sound, we don’t need to boot the server.</p>

<h3 id="variables-and-scope">Variables and Scope</h3>

<p>Here we encounter the first inconvenient.
In <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SC</a> there are some special pre-defined variables.
Each single character variable is pre-defined and globally available.
If you come from a modern programming language, this is strange.
However, it is often useful for prototyping in <a href="https://supercollider.github.io/">SC</a>.
A very special variable is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">s</code>, because it holds a reference to the default local server.
Therefore, to start the audio server, we evaluate:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">s</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">boot</span><span class="p">();</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>No one stops you from overwriting <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">s</code>, but I would not recommend it.
To define a <strong>code-block</strong> we use round brackets.
We can use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code> without defining it because it is already defined for us.</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">(</span>
<span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="n">x</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Evaluating</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">variable</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>results in an error because <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">variable</code> is undefined.
The following works just fine.</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">variable</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="n">variable</span><span class="p">;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Since <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code> is a global variable we can use it everywhere.
Evaluating the line and the code block will return <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">13</code>.</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">(</span>
<span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mf">3</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="n">x</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>but we can also define a local <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code>:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">(</span>
<span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mf">3</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="n">x</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Evaluating all these lines will return <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">3</code>, but the global variable <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code> is still <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">10</code>.
The following lines cause an error</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">variable</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">(</span>
<span class="n">variable</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">variable</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mf">3</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="n">variable</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>while the next lines work and return <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">13</code>.</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">(</span>
<span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">variable</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="n">variable</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">variable</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mf">3</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="n">variable</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>To define a new global variable, the variable name has to start with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">~</code>, for example,</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">(</span>
<span class="vg">~variable</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">(</span>
<span class="vg">~variable</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="vg">~variable</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mf">3</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="vg">~variable</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>returns <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">13</code>.</p>

<h3 id="functions">Functions</h3>

<p>To define a function, we encapsulate its content by curly brackets, and to execute it, we call <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">value()</code> on it:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">(</span>
<span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">func</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">};</span>
<span class="n">func</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">value</span><span class="p">();</span>      <span class="c1">// returns 10</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here we see another strange behavior: The last line of a function is its return value.
I am not a fan of this shortcut and if you work with <strong>cslang</strong> you will encounter additional ones.
It adds required knowledge to understand a program written in <strong>cslang</strong> and steepen the learning curve.
After getting used to it, they speed up the coding a little bit.</p>

<p>Here is another example of a function with arguments:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">(</span>
<span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">add</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="k">arg</span> <span class="n">a</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">b</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">b</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">};</span>
<span class="n">add</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">value</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">11</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="c1">// returns 17</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Like in Python, one can define a default value for each argument, and we can ignore the order if we add the names.
Furthermore, there is another rather strange shortcut:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">(</span>
<span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">add</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="o">|</span><span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">5</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">b</span><span class="o">|</span>
  <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">b</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">};</span>
<span class="n">add</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">value</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">b:</span> <span class="mf">11</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="c1">// returns 17</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>There are many other parts of the <strong>cslang</strong>, and if you want to get started, I encourage you to visit the tutorials of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/elifieldsteel">Eli Fieldsteel</a> or look at the official documentation.</p>

<h3 id="a-first-sine-wave">A First Sine Wave</h3>

<p>Let us create the most simple sound possible: a sine wave.
First, we define a function that can be seen as a process called <em>unit generator</em> (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">UGen</code>) that starts when we call <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">play()</code>.
There are hundred of different <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">UGens</code>s, they basically spit out real numbers over time.
For example <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SineOsc</code> samples a sine wave.</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="vg">~sine</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="k">arg</span> <span class="n">freq</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">freq</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nl">mul:</span> <span class="mf">0.2</span><span class="p">)};</span>
<span class="vg">~sineplay</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="vg">~sine</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">play</span><span class="p">();</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>By default, the sine wave oscillates between <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-1</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1</code>.
We define a frequency of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">200</code> Hz that is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">200</code> cycles per second and a multiple of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0.2</code> such that the amplitude stays between <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-0.2</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0.2</code>, which reduces the volume.
Note we that the following two statements are equivalent:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">freq</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nl">mul:</span> <span class="mf">0.2</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">freq</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mf">0.2</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>We can change all arguments we defined, for exmple,</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="vg">~sineplay</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sx">\freq</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">500</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>changes sets the frequence to 500 cycles per second which increases the pitch.</p>

<p>Note that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">set()</code> is not called on the function but on the return value of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">~sine.play()</code>!
In fact, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">play()</code> is another shortcut to play sound, and behind the scene, it creates a new <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code> which I will show in a moment.
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">play()</code> is excellent to play around and finding a sound, but once you have an idea which direction you want to go, it is better to define a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code>.</p>

<p>To stop the process, i.e., the sine wave, we can call:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="vg">~sineplay</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">release</span><span class="p">();</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Of course, you can also press <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cmd + .</code>, but this will kill all sound not only this sine wave.</p>

<h3 id="combining-sine-waves">Combining Sine Waves</h3>

<p>Let us define a slightly more complex sound generated by two sine waves:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="vg">~twosines</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="k">arg</span> <span class="n">freq1</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">freq2</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="mf">0.2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">freq1</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mf">0.2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">freq2</span><span class="p">)};</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>What do we expect to hear?
Since we add two identical sine waves together, we should hear the same sound but twice as load.
But if we play the sound, it does not fulfill our expectations:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="vg">~twosines</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">play</span><span class="p">();</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The reason is another inconvenience: <strong>sclang</strong> strictly evaluates everything from left to right.
For example, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">3 + 5 * 3</code> returns <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">24</code> instead of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">18</code>.
Therefore, we have to use brackets.
A very useful tool is the build in plotting tool.
We can see the problem more clearly if we plot our function:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="vg">~twosines</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">plot</span><span class="p">();</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>To achieve the desired result, we have to correct the code.</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="vg">~sinesplay</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="k">arg</span> <span class="n">freq1</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">freq2</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">freq1</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">freq:</span><span class="n">freq2</span><span class="p">))}.</span><span class="n">play</span><span class="p">()</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>or</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="vg">~sinesplay</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="k">arg</span> <span class="n">freq1</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">freq2</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">freq1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nl">mul:</span><span class="mf">0.2</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">freq:</span><span class="n">freq2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nl">mul:</span><span class="mf">0.2</span><span class="p">)}.</span><span class="n">play</span><span class="p">()</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h3 id="a-wobbling-sound">A Wobbling Sound</h3>

<p>Ok, this is rather boring.
However, if we change <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">freq2</code> such that it is not equal but close to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">freq1</code>, we get some interesting effect.
You may want to think about what sound you will hear if you do the following:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="vg">~sineplay</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sx">\freq2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">201</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>We hear a kind of wobble effect.
Why?
Well, two sine waves can add up, but they also can cancel each other out.
For example, if we add two sine waves but with phase <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pi</code>, we hear nothing.
This effect is used for noise cancelation in modern headphones.
Apart from some numerical errors, plotting the result reveals the cancelation:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{</span><span class="k">arg</span> <span class="n">freq1</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">freq2</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">freq1</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">freq:</span><span class="n">freq2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nl">phase:</span><span class="mf">pi</span><span class="p">))}.</span><span class="n">plot</span><span class="p">()</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Now back to the wobble effect.
Since <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">freq2</code> is 1 Hz higher than <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">freq1</code>, the second sine wave does one extra cycle for each second.
Therefore, in that time span, the two waves interact between adding up and cancel each other out.
I encourage you to play around.
What will happen if <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">freq2</code> is 5 Hz higher?
How does this affect the result?</p>

<h3 id="definition-of-a-synth">Definition of a Synth</h3>

<p>Here, I will not go into details because the documentation does a better job than I could ever accomplish.
In the following code snippet, I define a  <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code>.
The first argument of the method used to define the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code> is its name. 
The second one is its content.
I call <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">add()</code> to add the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code> to the audio server.
You could also call <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">store()</code>, which additionally stores the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code> in a file.
In this way, you can use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code> by loading it from a file and with some extra work, we can use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code> by
other tools like <a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">Sonic Pi</a>!!!</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">(</span>
<span class="nc">SynthDef</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="kr">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sx">\sinewaves</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="k">arg</span> <span class="n">freq1</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">freq2</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">205</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">amp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">0.4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">out</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">sig</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">amp</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mf">0.5</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">freq1</span><span class="p">);</span>
  <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">amp</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mf">0.5</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">freq:</span><span class="n">freq2</span><span class="p">));</span>
  <span class="nc">Out</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">out</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">sig</span><span class="err">!</span><span class="mf">2</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="p">}).</span><span class="n">add</span><span class="p">();</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>So far, the sound does only come out of one speaker.
The line</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">Out</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">out</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">sig</span><span class="err">!</span><span class="mf">2</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><strong>copies</strong> the sound and sends it to both speakers.
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sig!2</code> is another handy shortcut for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sig.dup(2)</code>.
Note that there is no re-evaluation happening, it just copies the result, but we can copy a function!
For example:</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="mf">5</span><span class="err">!</span><span class="mf">8</span>             <span class="c1">// returns [5, 5, 5, 5, 5, 5, 5, 5]</span>
<span class="p">[</span><span class="mf">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">3</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">4</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="err">!</span><span class="mf">3</span>     <span class="c1">// returns [[1,2,3,4], [1,2,3,4], [1,2,3,4]]</span>
<span class="n">rrand</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="err">!</span><span class="mf">3</span>   <span class="c1">// returns an array containing three equal elements!</span>
<span class="p">{</span><span class="n">rrand</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">)}</span><span class="err">!</span><span class="mf">3</span> <span class="c1">// returns an array containing three possible different elements!</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>After we defined the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code> using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SynthDef</code>, we can create it, which will immediately start the sound.
We can change all arguments during the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code> lifetime.</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="vg">~sinewaves</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">Synth</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sx">\sinewaves</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="vg">~sinewaves</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sx">\freq1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">100</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="vg">~sinewaves</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sx">\amp</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.2</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h3 id="envelopes-finite-ugens">Envelopes (Finite UGens)</h3>

<p>So far, we had to start and stop the sound by hand.
However, if we want to design a musical instrument, we want to manipulate the amplitude over time.
Imagine a piano: if we hit a key, the sound requires some time to reach its maximum amplitude.
This period is called <em>attacktime</em>.
After the maximum is reached, it decreases, and if the pianist releases the key, the sound vanishes completely.
There are infinite possibilities. For example, sometimes we want a sustaining sound, i.e., the amplitude stays constant for some period.</p>

<p>Instead of <em>maipulation</em> musicians use the term <em>modulation</em>.
In general, to achieve more interesing sounds modulation of different arguments is a good practice.
In the following I define an envelope (which I think of as a finite <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">UGen</code>).</p>

<p>Instead of manipulation, musicians use the term modulation.
In general, achieving more interesting sound modulation of different arguments is a good practice.
In the following, I define an envelope (which I think of as a finite <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">UGen</code>).</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{</span><span class="nc">EnvGen</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">kr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nc">Env</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="kr">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">levels:</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="nl">times:</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="mf">0.1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">0.4</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">0.1</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="nl">curve:</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="mf">2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">-3</span><span class="p">]))}.</span><span class="n">plot</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.6</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<div><img style="height:300px;" src="/Pages/assets/images/envelope-plot.png" alt="Env" /></div>

<p>The envelope starts at <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0</code>, increases to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1</code> during <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0.1</code> seconds, drops to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0.4</code> in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0.4</code> seconds, and then drops to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0</code> in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0.1</code> seconds.
The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">curve</code> argument influences curvature of the segments.
It can be best understood by plotting the result while playing around with the values.</p>

<p>By multiplying the signal of the envelope to our sound signal, we get a sound that stops after <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0.6</code> seconds.</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">(</span>
<span class="nc">SynthDef</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="kr">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sx">\sinewaves</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="k">arg</span> <span class="n">freq1</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">freq2</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">205</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">amp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">0.4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">out</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">sig</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">env</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="c1">// doneAction: 2 removes the Synth from the server/memory if it is done!</span>
  <span class="n">env</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">EnvGen</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">kr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nc">Env</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="kr">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">levels:</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="nl">times:</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="mf">0.01</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">0.2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">0.1</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="nl">curve:</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="mf">2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">-3</span><span class="p">]),</span> <span class="nl">doneAction:</span> <span class="nc">Done</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">freeSelf</span><span class="p">);</span>
  <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">amp</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mf">0.5</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">freq1</span><span class="p">);</span>
  <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">amp</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mf">0.5</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">freq:</span><span class="n">freq2</span><span class="p">));</span>
  <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">env</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="nc">Out</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">out</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">sig</span><span class="err">!</span><span class="mf">2</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="p">}).</span><span class="n">add</span><span class="p">();</span>
<span class="p">)</span>

<span class="vg">~sinewaves</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">Synth</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sx">\sinewaves</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Let’s plot the sound with and without multiplied by the envelop:</p>

<div><img style="height:300px;" src="/Pages/assets/images/synth-plot.png" alt="Synth" /></div>
<div><img style="height:300px;" src="/Pages/assets/images/synth-and-envelope-plot.png" alt="Synth with Env" /></div>

<p>The following code generates the plot.</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">(</span>
<span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">sig</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">env</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">freq1</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">200</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">freq2</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">205</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">amp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">0.4</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="n">env</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="nc">EnvGen</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">kr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nc">Env</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="kr">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">levels:</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="nl">times:</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mf">0.1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">0.4</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">0.1</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="nl">curve:</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mf">2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">-3</span><span class="p">]))};</span>

  <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">amp</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mf">0.5</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">freq1</span><span class="p">);</span>
  <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">amp</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mf">0.5</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">freq:</span><span class="n">freq2</span><span class="p">));</span>
  <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">sig</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">env</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="n">sig</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}.</span><span class="n">plot</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.6</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h3 id="explore-new-sounds">Explore New Sounds</h3>

<p>To get a feeling for how a sound changes using different arguments, I recommend to use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">play()</code> in combination of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MouseX</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MouseY</code>.
The latter two <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">UGen</code>s spit out values that depend on the position of your mouse curser.
Therefore, you can easily change two independently arguments at the same time.</p>

<p>To get a feeling for how a sound changes using different arguments, I recommend using play() in a combination of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MouseX</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MouseY</code>.
The latter two UGens spit out values that depend on the position of your mouse cursor.
Therefore, you can easily change two independent arguments at the same time.</p>

<div class="language-supercollider highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nc">MouseX</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">kr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">500</span><span class="p">))</span><span class="err">!</span><span class="mf">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mf">0.5</span> <span class="p">}.</span><span class="n">play</span><span class="p">()</span>

<span class="p">{</span> <span class="nc">LPF</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">in:</span> <span class="nc">Saw</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nc">MouseX</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">kr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">10</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">500</span><span class="p">))</span><span class="err">!</span><span class="mf">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mf">0.2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nl">freq:</span> <span class="nc">MouseY</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">kr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">5000</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">}.</span><span class="n">play</span><span class="p">()</span>

<span class="p">{</span> <span class="nc">LPF</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">in:</span> <span class="nc">WhiteNoise</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">mul:</span> <span class="mf">0.2</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="nl">freq:</span> <span class="nc">MouseX</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">kr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">500</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">}.</span><span class="n">play</span><span class="p">()</span>

<span class="p">{</span> <span class="nc">LPF</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">in:</span> <span class="nc">WhiteNoise</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">mul:</span> <span class="mf">0.4</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="nl">freq:</span> <span class="mf">1000</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">EnvGen</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nc">Env</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">perc</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.7</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">}.</span><span class="n">play</span><span class="p">()</span>

<span class="p">{</span> <span class="nc">EnvGen</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nc">Env</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">perc</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.7</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">}.</span><span class="n">plot</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.8</span><span class="p">);</span>

<span class="p">{</span> <span class="nc">SinOsc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">100</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nl">mul:</span> <span class="mf">0.2</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nc">LPF</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">in:</span> <span class="nc">WhiteNoise</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nl">mul:</span> <span class="mf">0.4</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="nl">freq:</span> <span class="mf">1000</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nc">EnvGen</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">ar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nc">Env</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">perc</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">0.1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">0.7</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">}.</span><span class="n">play</span><span class="p">();</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h3 id="composing">Composing</h3>

<p>Composing a whole piece takes time.
One way is first to design your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Synth</code>s or find proper samples.
Then we need a rhythm and/or melody.
For that purpose, we use some other tools, or we use <strong>sclang</strong>.
If you want to use <strong>sclang</strong> a good starting point is to look into the concept of <em>pattern</em> especially <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PBind</code>.</p>

<p>To get a better feeling of what is possible, copy the following <a href="http://sccode.org/1-5bF">code</a> and execute it in the IDE.
The piece was composed by <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/elifieldsteel">Eli Fieldsteel</a> and makes use of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wavetable_synthesis#:~:text=Wavetable%20synthesis%20is%20fundamentally%20based,selects%20the%20single%20cycle%20waveform.">wavetable synthesis</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Benedikt Zönnchen</name><email>benedikt.zoennchen@web.de</email></author><category term="Music" /><category term="SuperCollider" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the past, I did a 15-minute introduction for SuperCollider (SC) for students at my University. Likewise to Sonic Pi’s introduction, I will repeat everything I talked about and give some additional insights.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Live Performance with Sonic Pi</title><link href="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/03/25/sonic-pi-in-15-minutes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Live Performance with Sonic Pi" /><published>2021-03-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-03-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/03/25/sonic-pi-in-15-minutes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bzoennchen.github.io//Pages/2021/03/25/sonic-pi-in-15-minutes.html"><![CDATA[<p>In the past I did a 15 minute introduction for <a href="https://sonic-pi.net/">Sonic Pi</a> for students at my University.
In the following text I want to give the same short introduction either for students to look the information up or for people interested in algorithmic composition.
The aim here is to show how easy it is to make a beat in Sonic Pi.
The implementation is inspired by <a href="https://learningmusic.ableton.com/make-beats/make-beats.html">the beat grid</a>.</p>

<h2 id="building-a-beat">Building a Beat</h2>

<p>First we define an array containing different drum-like samples.
These samples come with Sonic Pi but you can extend the sample library by your own samples.</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">instruments</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span>
  <span class="ss">:bd_haus</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="c1">#1</span>
  <span class="ss">:sn_zome</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="c1">#2</span>
  <span class="ss">:drum_cymbal_closed</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="c1">#3</span>
  <span class="ss">:drum_cymbal_pedal</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="ss">:drum_bass_soft</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="ss">:drum_bass_hard</span>
<span class="p">]</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>We build a four by four beat, i.e., one unit is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0.25</code> beat.
The beat is modelled by an array of length <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">16</code>.</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">beats1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span>
  <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span>
<span class="p">]</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The idea is to address a specific sample by a number between <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6</code>.
Zero means silence!
Therefore, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">beat1</code> starts with the sample <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">:bd_haus</code> followed by silence followed by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">:bd_haus</code> and so on.</p>

<p>To run the beat we define a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">live_loop</code> which is a special thread of Sonic Pi.
The content of the thread can be updated dynamically, that is, the user can</p>

<ol>
  <li>change the content,</li>
  <li>re-evaluate,</li>
</ol>

<p>and the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">live_loop</code> will change accordingly.
In the loop/thread we iterate from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">i = 0 ... 15</code>.
For each iteration we play the beat according to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">beat1</code> and sleep for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0.25</code> beat, since we want to have a 4 times 4 beat.</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">live_loop</span> <span class="ss">:drummer1</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="mi">16</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">times</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">|</span>
    <span class="n">sample</span> <span class="n">instruments</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">beats1</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">beats1</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
    <span class="nb">sleep</span> <span class="mf">0.25</span>
  <span class="k">end</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="building-a-melody">Building a Melody</h2>

<p>To bring a little more dynamic into the piece, we introduce a randomly generated melody.
In algorithmic composition we have to find a balance between complete chaos and structure.
To much chaos will sound unpleasant while too much structure is boring.
Therefore, I shuffle a specific scale which gives us notes that fit together:</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">melody</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">shuffle</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">scale</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">:e4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:minor</span><span class="p">))</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>To play the melody we need another <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">live_loop</code>.
Furthermore, I use a simple sine wave for the melody.
Also note that we play the first and second harmonic as well such that the sound is a little more complex.
It is still very simple!</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">use_synth</span> <span class="ss">:sine</span>

<span class="n">live_loop</span> <span class="ss">:pianist</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="n">play</span> <span class="n">melody</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">tick</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">amp: </span><span class="mf">0.4</span>
  <span class="n">play</span> <span class="n">melody</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">look</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">12</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">amp: </span><span class="mf">0.3</span>
  <span class="n">play</span> <span class="n">melody</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">look</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">24</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">amp: </span><span class="mf">0.2</span>
  <span class="nb">sleep</span> <span class="mf">0.5</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="building-another-beat">Building another Beat</h2>

<p>Finally, we add another beat and therefore another <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">live_loop</code>:</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">beats2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span>
  <span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">5</span>
<span class="p">]</span>

<span class="n">live_loop</span> <span class="ss">:drummer2</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="mi">16</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">times</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">|</span>
    <span class="n">sample</span> <span class="n">instruments</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">beats2</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">beats2</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
    <span class="nb">sleep</span> <span class="mf">0.25</span>
  <span class="k">end</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>And we change the beat per minute to 98 which speeds up the whole piece:</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">use_bpm</span> <span class="mi">98</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="putting-everything-together">Putting everything together</h2>

<p>The complete code is given by the following listing:</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">use_bpm</span> <span class="mi">98</span>

<span class="n">use_synth</span> <span class="ss">:sine</span>

<span class="n">instruments</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span>
  <span class="ss">:bd_haus</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="c1">#1</span>
  <span class="ss">:sn_zome</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="c1">#2</span>
  <span class="ss">:drum_cymbal_closed</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="c1">#3</span>
  <span class="ss">:drum_cymbal_pedal</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="ss">:drum_bass_soft</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="ss">:drum_bass_hard</span>
<span class="p">]</span>

<span class="n">beats1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span>
  <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span>
<span class="p">]</span>

<span class="n">beats2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span>
  <span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">5</span>
<span class="p">]</span>

<span class="n">melody</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">shuffle</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">scale</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">:e4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:minor</span><span class="p">))</span>

<span class="n">live_loop</span> <span class="ss">:pianist</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="n">play</span> <span class="n">melody</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">tick</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">amp: </span><span class="mf">0.4</span>
  <span class="n">play</span> <span class="n">melody</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">look</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">12</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">amp: </span><span class="mf">0.3</span>
  <span class="n">play</span> <span class="n">melody</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">look</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">24</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">amp: </span><span class="mf">0.2</span>
  <span class="nb">sleep</span> <span class="mf">0.5</span>
<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="n">live_loop</span> <span class="ss">:drummer1</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="mi">16</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">times</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">|</span>
    <span class="n">sample</span> <span class="n">instruments</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">beats1</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">beats1</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
    <span class="nb">sleep</span> <span class="mf">0.25</span>
  <span class="k">end</span>
<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="n">live_loop</span> <span class="ss">:drummer2</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="mi">16</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">times</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">|</span>
    <span class="n">sample</span> <span class="n">instruments</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">beats2</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">beats2</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
    <span class="nb">sleep</span> <span class="mf">0.25</span>
  <span class="k">end</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="performing-live">Performing Live</h2>

<p>Of course this gets boring pretty fast but now we can start our live programming to change the sound over time.
For example we can start by one beat, after a while start the second and the melody.
Then we might want to change the melody, for example, the scale.
We can change the beats as well and introduce complete new elements.
Time to play ;)!</p>]]></content><author><name>Benedikt Zönnchen</name><email>benedikt.zoennchen@web.de</email></author><category term="Music" /><category term="Sonic-Pi" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the past I did a 15 minute introduction for Sonic Pi for students at my University. In the following text I want to give the same short introduction either for students to look the information up or for people interested in algorithmic composition. The aim here is to show how easy it is to make a beat in Sonic Pi. The implementation is inspired by the beat grid.]]></summary></entry></feed>